<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://curl.group/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://curl.group/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-06T10:26:49+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/feed.xml</id><title type="html">CURL</title><subtitle>Research Group</subtitle><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><entry><title type="html">Spatial Curvature from Super-Hubble Cosmological Fluctuations</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2023/12/01/2302.14530.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spatial Curvature from Super-Hubble Cosmological Fluctuations" /><published>2023-12-01T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-01T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2023/12/01/2302.14530</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2023/12/01/2302.14530.html"><![CDATA[<p>Could cosmological perturbations stretched over distances larger than
the size of the observable Universe modify the shape of our
space-time? <a href="/members/blachier.html"><strong>Baptiste</strong></a>,
<a href="/members/auclair.html"><strong>Pierre</strong></a>
and <a href="/members/chris.html"><strong>Christophe</strong></a>, in collaboration with
<a href="https://www.lpens.ens.psl.eu/vincent-vennin/?lang=en"><strong>Vincent Vennin</strong></a>, have
recently shown that this is the case through the spatial curvature.</p>

<p>It is a common Cosmologist’s intuition that cosmological fluctuations,
the tiny perturbations of amplitude \(10^{-5}\) at the origin of
galaxies, should induce some kind of noise on the cosmological
parameters. Is this quantifiable? Are super-Hubble cosmological
perturbations having an effect at all?</p>

<p>In Ref. <a class="citation" href="#blachier:2023ooc">[1]</a>, we show that arbitrarily long
perturbations have an observable effect. More precisely, the gradient
and Laplacian of these fluctuations are dynamically <strong>creating a
spatial curvature</strong> in the homogeneous and isotropic metric of local
observers. In the following picture, we sketch how one of these modes,
having a wavelength much larger than the observer’s Hubble radius, can
be “felt” through its gradient.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2302.14530/cosmograd.png" alt="grad" title="Super-Hubble gradient" /></p>

<p>It is not a few Hubble-sized fluctuations that contribute, but an infinite
number of super-Hubble modes, all those having wavelength larger than our observable
universe. Denoting by \(K\) the curvature of the FLRW spatial sections,
and \(\xi\) the sum of these constant modes, we find</p>

\[K = -\frac{2}{3} \Delta \xi - \frac{1}{3} \left(\nabla \xi \right)^2.\]

<p>However, because fluctuations are, by definition, of random nature, we
cannot predict a definite value for the curvature density parameter
\(\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}\). This one is now promoted to a stochastic
variable. Even though the sum of all super-Hubble modes averages to
zero, i.e. \(\langle \xi \rangle = 0\), we predict, for the standard
Gaussian and scale-invariant cosmological perturbations, a very small
non-vanishing value</p>

\[\langle \Omega_\mathrm{K_0} \rangle = -\frac{\langle K e^{-2\xi} \rangle}{a_0^2 H_0^2} = \frac{5}{6} \mathcal{P}_* \simeq 1.7 \times 10^{-9}.\]

<p>More importantly, because \(\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}\) is a stochastic
variable, it also fluctuates and its realizations are, in fact,
dictated by its standard deviation</p>

\[\sqrt{\langle{\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}^2}\rangle-\langle{\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}}\rangle^2} \simeq \dfrac{1}{3}
\sqrt{\mathcal{P}_*} \simeq 1.5 \times 10^{-5}.\]

<p>This is the <strong>typical value</strong> that any observer will measure <strong>at any
epoch</strong> during the cosmic history.</p>

<hr />

<p>But there is more. The spatial curvature of our local Hubble patch is
thus a measurable number that can tell us what is going on on the
largest possible length scales of the Universe, length scales that are
much larger than our Hubble volume. What if the infinite sum of very
large wavelength modes, \(\xi\) here, is no longer a small
quantity? Such a situation could very well be happening if the
Universe has experienced a period of stochastic inflation in its
infancy!</p>

<p>In Ref. <a class="citation" href="#blachier:2023ooc">[1]</a>, we have been able to estimate the
full probability distribution function for \(\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}\)
when cosmological fluctuations are generated by Cosmic Inflation. If
\(\xi\) remains small, it is a slightly distorted Gaussian
distribution with a typical width of \(10^{-5}\), as expected. But if
inflation last for a long period, enough for \(\xi\) to be of order
unity, the distribution becomes highly non-Gaussian, as represented in
the following figure (red curve)</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2302.14530/probomega_tails.jpg" alt="proba" title="Non-Gaussian probability distribution" /></p>

<p>In this plot, the black curve is what would be a Gaussian probability
distribution with same width. Clearly, large values of
\(\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}\) are now much more probable than what one could
have naively expected. Are we going to measure a non-vanishing
\(\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}\) in the future?</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Could cosmological perturbations stretched over distances larger than the size of the observable Universe modify the shape of our space-time? Baptiste, Pierre and Christophe, in collaboration with Vincent Vennin, have recently shown that this is the case through the spatial curvature.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2023/11/17/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2023-11-17T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-17T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2023/11/17/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2023/11/17/seminar.html"><![CDATA[<p>The next cosmology seminar takes place on <strong>Friday 24th</strong> of November,
seminar <strong>room E349</strong> at <strong>2pm</strong>. Our guest speaker will be <strong>Bryce
Cyr</strong> from the <a href="https://www.jodrellbank.manchester.ac.uk/"><strong>Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics</strong></a> at the University
of Manchester (Manchester, United Kingdom).</p>

<hr />

<p>At 2pm, room E349,  <strong>Bryce Cyr</strong> (University of Manchester), will be talking about</p>

<h3 id="synergies-between-gravitational-waves-and-cmb-spectral-distortions">Synergies between gravitational waves and CMB spectral distortions</h3>

<p><em>In this talk, I will discuss various ways in which distortions to the
 frequency spectrum of the cosmic microwave background can be used to
 place constraints on stochastic backgrounds of gravitational
 waves. After a brief overview of spectral distortion theory, I will
 show how enhancements to the small-scale primordial power spectrum of
 curvature perturbations can induce sizeable distortions. Even in the
 absence of enhancements, a nearly-scale invariant spectrum presents a
 target well within reach of next generation
 experiments. Additionally, I will highlight how the presence of
 primordial tensor modes will also lead to an inevitable (although
 small) distortion signature. I will then apply this formalism to a
 model of scalar induced gravitational waves (SIGWs), showcasing how
 constraints on the primordial scalar power spectrum can be mapped to
 the gravitational wave parameter space for these models. Time
 permitting, I will also show our updated formalism can be used to
 improve constraints on the parameter space of primordial black
 holes.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The next cosmology seminar takes place on Friday 24th of November, seminar room E349 at 2pm. Our guest speaker will be Bryce Cyr from the Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics at the University of Manchester (Manchester, United Kingdom).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2023/10/11/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2023-10-11T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-11T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2023/10/11/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2023/10/11/seminar.html"><![CDATA[<p>The next cosmology seminar takes place on <strong>Thursday 2nd</strong> of
November, seminar <strong>room E349</strong> at <strong>2pm</strong>. Our guest speaker will be
<strong>Suvashis Maity</strong> from the Indian Institute of Technology (IIT)
Madras (Chennai, India).</p>

<hr />

<p>At 2pm, room E349,  Suvashis Maity (IIT Madras), will be talking about</p>

<h3 id="ultra-slow-roll-inflation-and-loop-corrections-to-the-scalar-power-spectrum">Ultra slow roll inflation and loop corrections to the scalar power spectrum</h3>

<p><em>Recently, there have been efforts to examine the contributions to the
 scalar power spectrum due to the loops arising from the cubic order
 terms in the action describing the perturbations, specifically in
 inflationary scenarios that permit a brief epoch of ultra slow roll
 (USR). A phase of USR inflation leads to significant observational
 consequences, such as the copious production of primordial black
 holes. In this talk, I shall discuss the loop contributions to the
 scalar power spectrum in scenarios of USR inflation arising due to
 the quartic order terms in the action describing the scalar
 perturbations. I shall initially describe the computation of the loop
 contributions to the scalar power spectrum due to the dominant term
 in the action at the quartic order. Thereafter, I shall consider a
 scenario wherein a phase of USR is sandwiched between two stages of
 slow roll inflation and describe the behavior of the loop
 contributions in situations involving late, intermediate and early
 epochs of USR. In the inflationary scenario involving a late phase of
 USR, for reasonable choices of the parameters, I shall show that the
 loop corrections are negligible for the entire range of wave
 numbers. In the intermediate case, the contributions from the loops
 prove to be scale invariant over large scales, and we find that these
 contributions can amount to 30% of the power spectrum at the leading
 order. In the case wherein USR sets in early, we find that the loop
 contributions could be negative and can dominate the power spectrum
 at the leading order, which indicates a breakdown of the perturbative
 expansion. I shall conclude with a brief summary and outlook.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The next cosmology seminar takes place on Thursday 2nd of November, seminar room E349 at 2pm. Our guest speaker will be Suvashis Maity from the Indian Institute of Technology (IIT) Madras (Chennai, India).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Découverte du fond stochastique d’ondes gravitationnelles</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2023/07/03/SGWB.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Découverte du fond stochastique d’ondes gravitationnelles" /><published>2023-07-03T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-07-03T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2023/07/03/SGWB</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2023/07/03/SGWB.html"><![CDATA[<p>Plusieurs collaborations internationales en
<a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radioastronomie"><strong>radio-astronomie</strong></a>
viennent d’annoncer la première détection du <strong>fond stochastique
d’ondes gravitationnelles</strong>. <a href="/members/auclair.html"><strong>Pierre</strong></a> a
cosigné la publication de
l’<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_Pulsar_Timing_Array"><strong>EPTA</strong></a>.</p>

<p>Ce <strong>jeudi 29 Juin 2023</strong>, plusieurs collaborations internationales en
radio-astronomie,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_American_Nanohertz_Observatory_for_Gravitational_Waves"><strong>NANOGRAV</strong></a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_Pulsar_Timing_Array"><strong>EPTA</strong></a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parkes_Observatory#Parkes_Pulsar_Timing_Array"><strong>PPTA</strong></a>,
<a href="https://inpta.iitr.ac.in/"><strong>InPTA</strong></a> et
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five-hundred-meter_Aperture_Spherical_Telescope"><strong>CPTA</strong></a>,
ont annoncé avoir détecté indépendamment un <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravitational_wave_background"><strong>fond stochastique
d’ondes
gravitationnelles</strong></a>
dans une bande de fréquences située autour du milliardième de
Hertz. C’est une découverte majeure qui devrait nous permettre d’en
apprendre beaucoup sur la formation des galaxies et sur la physique a
l’œuvre dans tout l’Univers.</p>

<p>Les contributions de <a href="/members/auclair.html"><strong>Pierre</strong></a> à la
publication de EPTA, Ref. <a class="citation" href="#antoniadis:2023xlr">[1]</a>, concernent l’analyse des
différentes sources cosmologiques possibles, dont les
<strong>cordes cosmiques</strong>, un des domaines d’expertise de <a href="/"><strong>CURL</strong></a>.</p>

<p>Le <strong>fond stochastique d’ondes gravitationnelles</strong> est la
superposition de toutes les ondes gravitationnelles émises dans
l’univers. Par analogie avec le son, c’est comme si nous avions etendu
le brouhaha d’une foule sans toutefois parvenir à distinguer une
conversation en particulier. Ce bruit de fond est très intéressant car
il donne accès aux propriétés stochastiques et globales de toutes les
sources à la fois.</p>

<p>Tout aussi spectaculaire que cette découverte est la méthode utilisée
pour trouver ce fond d’ondes gravitationnelles. Point de détecteurs
terrestres ou spatiaux, mais des <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%89toile_%C3%A0_neutrons"><strong>étoiles à
neutrons</strong></a>
particulières. Une étoile à neutron est le cœur chaud et ulta-dense
qu’il reste après qu’une étoile supermassive (entre 10 et 20 fois la
masse du Soleil) ait explosé en supernova. La fameuse <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/N%C3%A9buleuse_du_Crabe"><strong>nébuleuse du
Crabe</strong></a>, un
rémanent de supernova, contient un pulsar en son centre.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/outreach/m1_HaSIIOIII_cut.jpg" alt="M1, la nébuleuse du Crabe" /></p>

<p>Les <strong>réseaux de pulsars millisecondes</strong>, ou <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pulsar_timing_array"><strong>Pulsar Timing
Arrays</strong></a> (PTA) en
anglais, utilisent des étoiles à neutrons tournant très rapidement sur
elles-même, plusieurs centaines de fois par seconde, qui émettent un
fort rayonnement dans la direction de leur axe magnétique. À la
manière d’un phare, le <strong>pulsar</strong> semble avoir une <em>pulsation</em> lorsque
ce rayonnement radio se trouve en direction de la Terre.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/outreach/pulsar.gif" alt="Un pulsar" /></p>

<p>La pulsation très régulière des pulsars en font des horloges célestes
extrêmement précises. En observant ces pulsars pendant plus de vingt ans
au moyen de radiotélescopes, et en notant soigneusement les petites
irrégularités dans les temps d’arrivée de leur flash, les
radioastronomes sont parvenus à mettre en évidence l’existence de ce
fond stochastique d’ondes gravitationnelles. En effet, lorsque ces
ondes gravitationnelles passent entre la Terre et les pulsars, elles
induisent des déformations de l’espace-temps qui laissent une
corrélation caractéristique entre les temps d’arrivée des flashs.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/outreach/hellings_downs_correlations.jpg" alt="Corrélations de Hellings and Downs" /></p>

<p>Si la nature “onde gravitationnelle” de ce signal est donc établie,
plusieurs interprétations sont néanmoins possibles concernant son
origine. L’hypothèse présentée comme la plus naturelle est celle d’un
fond stochastique dû à des binaires de trous noirs
supermassifs. D’autres propositions, comme les cordes cosmiques ou les
transitions de phases du premier ordre, permettraient aussi
d’expliquer les observations, avec d’importantes conséquences pour
notre compréhension des premiers instants de l’Univers.</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Plusieurs collaborations internationales en radio-astronomie viennent d’annoncer la première détection du fond stochastique d’ondes gravitationnelles. Pierre a cosigné la publication de l’EPTA.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Euclid sur les starting blocks</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2023/06/23/EuclidBxe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Euclid sur les starting blocks" /><published>2023-06-23T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-06-23T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2023/06/23/EuclidBxe</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2023/06/23/EuclidBxe.html"><![CDATA[<p>Le télescope spatial
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euclid_(spacecraft)"><strong>Euclid</strong></a> de
l’Agence Spatiale Européenne est sur les starting blocks. Les
scientifiques belges impliqués dans la mission donnent une conférence
de presse au Planétarium de Bruxelles. Rendez-vous <strong>lundi 26 juin</strong> à
<strong>10h</strong>.</p>

<p>Le lancement du satellite Euclid (ESA) est prévu pour le 1er juillet
2023 à 17h11 (CEST) depuis Cap Canaveral, à suivre en direct sur
l’<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/ESA_Web_TV"><strong>ESA web
TV</strong></a>. D’ici là, une
conférence de presse est organisée au Planétarium de Bruxelles,
<strong>lundi 26 juin</strong> à <strong>10h</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="https://indico.cern.ch/event/1298261/"><strong>Inscriptions</strong></a> et <a href="https://owncloud.ulb.ac.be/index.php/s/SBnbtB5onJvaEFe"><strong>press release</strong></a></p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Le télescope spatial Euclid de l’Agence Spatiale Européenne est sur les starting blocks. Les scientifiques belges impliqués dans la mission donnent une conférence de presse au Planétarium de Bruxelles. Rendez-vous lundi 26 juin à 10h.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The opiparous edition of Encyclopædia Inflationaris</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2023/05/08/EI.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The opiparous edition of Encyclopædia Inflationaris" /><published>2023-05-08T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-05-08T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2023/05/08/EI</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2023/05/08/EI.html"><![CDATA[<p>We have released a new version of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1303.3787"><strong>Encyclopædia
Inflationaris</strong></a> and its associated
public code
<a href="https://github.com/cosmicinflation/aspic"><strong>ASPIC</strong></a>. This opiparous
edition extends the original paper by 400 pages and features 46 new
models of inflation that have been proposed in the last decade. Cosmic
Inflation is ready to tackle the data challenges of tomorrow.</p>

<p>The first edition of <strong>Encyclopædia Inflationaris</strong> was published in
Ref. <a class="citation" href="#martin:2014vha">[1]</a> and authored by <a href="https://inspirehep.net/authors/998637"><strong>Jérôme
Martin</strong></a>,
<a href="/members/chris.html"><strong>Christophe</strong></a> and <a href="https://www.lpens.ens.psl.eu/vincent-vennin/?lang=en"><strong>Vincent
Vennin</strong></a>. It
was built upon the slow-roll models of inflation proposed prior to
2013, the year of the first
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planck_(spacecraft)"><strong>Planck</strong></a> data
release. It contains accurate reheating-consistent slow-roll
calculations of the background universe and of the expected scalar and
tensor perturbations for all these models. Although it is now often
seen as a review, it is a genuine paper as it goes beyond the mere
gathering of known results. Indeed, a fair fraction of these models
had been studied only under rough approximations, which were not
matching the accuracy needed by the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB)
data. The ambition of the project was, and still is, to provide an
(almost) exact treatment of single-field inflationary models using
only the slow-roll approximation while incorporating the kinematic
effects of reheating.</p>

<p>All these results are also incorporated in a public runtime library,
<strong>ASPIC</strong> <a class="citation" href="#aspic">[2]</a>, which has been used in a number of
subsequent works. For instance, Bayesian model comparison using the
Planck CMB data has been presented in Refs. <a class="citation" href="#martin:2013nzq">[3]</a>
and <a class="citation" href="#martin:2014rqa">[4]</a> while the constraints derived on the
reheating epoch have been separately presented in Refs. <a class="citation" href="#martin:2014nya">[5]</a> and <a class="citation" href="#martin:2016oyk">[6]</a>.</p>

<hr />

<p>Ten years later Cosmic Inflation remains the most favoured scenario
of the early universe <a class="citation" href="#chowdhury:2019otk">[7]</a> but several
developments have called for the release of a new edition:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>First, at the theoretical level, new models have been proposed. Some
of them boil down to one of the functional forms of the inflationary
potentials already encoded in ASPIC, in which case they have been
added in the relevant sections<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Some other models give rise to
new inflationary potentials, and therefore constitute new sections
of Encyclopædia Inflationaris, as well as new entries in the ASPIC
library. There are 24 such new potential functions in the new
edition (here ordered alphabetically): <strong>Axion Hilltop Inflation</strong>
(AHI), <strong>Cubicly Corrected Starobinsky Inflation</strong> (CCSI),<strong>Double
Exponential Inflation</strong> (DEI), <strong>Dual Inflation</strong> (DI), <strong>Fibre
Inflation</strong> (FI), <strong>Generalized Double Well Inflation</strong> (GDWI),
<strong>Hyperbolic Inflation</strong> (HBI), <strong>Hybrid Natural Inflation</strong> (HNI),
<strong>Non-Renormalizable Corrected Loop Inflation</strong> (NCLI),
<strong>N-Formalism Inflation</strong> (NFI), <strong>Non-Minimal Large Field
Inflation</strong> (NMLFI), <strong>Pure Arctan Inflation</strong> (PAI), <strong>Radiatively
Corrected Inflection Point Inflation</strong> (RCIPI), <strong>Radiatively
Corrected Large Field Inflation</strong> (RCLFI), <strong>String Axion Inflation
I</strong> (SAII), <strong>String Axion Inflation II (SAIII), Super-conformal
Alpha Attractor A Inflation</strong> (SAAI), <strong>T-Model Inflation</strong> (TMI),
<strong>Super-conformal Alpha Attractor B Inflation</strong> (SABI),
<strong>Super-conformal Alpha Attractor T Inflation</strong> (SATI), <strong>Symmetry
Breaking Kähler Inflation</strong> (SBKI), <strong>S-Dual Inflation</strong> (SDI),
<strong>Smeared Higgs Inflation</strong> (SHI), <strong>Mukhanov Inflation</strong>
(VFMI). The inclusion of these models allows the new edition to
provide an up-to-date landscape of all single-field slow-roll
inflationary models, bringing the number of models included in the
<strong>ASPIC</strong> library to 118.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Second, at the observational level, the first edition compared the
predictions of single-field models with the early release of the
Planck 2013 data. Since then, additional data has been collected,
and the second edition features second-order slow-roll constraints
from the full <a href="https://pla.esac.esa.int"><strong>Planck Legacy +
Bicep-Keck</strong></a> data combination. The
Bayesian evidence of all models has also been re-computed with the
new data set, and the results will be presented in a separate
publication.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Third, as the accuracy of the recent data releases has kept
improving, several projects are on their way that should deliver
even more accurate cosmological data in the years to come. In
particular, let us mention ground-based experiments that are
currently operating such as <a href="http://bicepkeck.org/"><strong>BICEP3 &amp; Keck
array</strong></a> and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Pole_Telescope"><strong>SPT</strong></a> in
Antarctica,
<a href="https://research.iac.es/proyecto/quijote/pages/en/home.php"><strong>QUIJOTE</strong></a>
in the Canary islands, and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmology_Large_Angular_Scale_Surveyor"><strong>CLASS</strong></a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atacama_Cosmology_Telescope"><strong>ACT</strong></a>
and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/POLARBEAR"><strong>Polarbear</strong></a> in the
Atacama desert. They have been very recently joined by
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qubic_experiment"><strong>QUBIC</strong></a>. In
space, the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euclid_(spacecraft)"><strong>Euclid</strong></a>
satellite is soon to be launched and will provide unprecedented
measurements on the matter power spectrum, down to very small
scales. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LiteBIRD"><strong>LiteBIRD</strong></a>
satellite is planned to be launched in 2028 and should allow us to
further constrain the \(B\)-mode signal in the polarisation of the
CMB. These prospects of ever increasing precision confirm the
relevance of the original Encyclopædia Inflationaris and ASPIC
projects, namely the need for accurate predictions on a
model-to-model basis. For this reason, we have continued to pay
special attention to solve the inflationary dynamics exactly,
without any other approximations than those contained in the
slow-roll framework. This one has indeed been shown to be
sufficiently accurate for the Planck CMB data <a class="citation" href="#ringeval:2013lea">[8]</a> and can be extended to arbitrary precision if
needed <a class="citation" href="#auclair:2022yxs">[9]</a>. On the contrary, as discussed in
Ref. <a class="citation" href="#martin:2016iqo">[10]</a> other commonly-employed
approximations are now too imprecise to allow for a fair comparison
with the data.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>Some of the new models are compatible with the present data, as one
could have expected, but this statement is <strong>strongly</strong> reheating
dependent. This can be illustrated by the following figure. It shows
their predictions, namely spectral index \(n_\mathrm{S}\) and
tensor-to-scalar ratio \(r\) as a function of the reheating energy
scale \(E_{\mathrm{reh}}\) (assuming a matter-like reheating for
illustration purposes). The contours are the \(68\%\) and \(95\%\)
confidence intervals associated with the successive Planck data
releases since 2013.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/opiparous/nslogr_plc3_bkppol.png"><img src="/assets/images/opiparous/nslogr_plc3_bkppol.png" alt="nslogr" title="Spectral index and tensor-to-scalar ratio" /></a></p>

<p>As this figure shows, getting reheating-consistent predictions has
never been so crucial. The reheating expansion history determines the
part of the inflationary potential being probed by cosmological
measurements, it can now substantially affect the preference shown by
the data for a given model (in technical terms, the Bayesian
evidence). This is one of the reasons why, in the opirarous edition,
the <strong>Starobinsky model</strong> (SI) and <strong>Higgs Inflation</strong> (HI) are now
treated as distinct models, since they come with different reheating
histories. Moreover, even though they are often treated as sharing the
same potential, this is only correct at leading order in an expansion
with respect to the inverse of the non-minimal coupling of the
field. Differences arise at next-to-leading order that we now account
for in an exact manner.</p>

<p>The previous figure certainly confirms the strategy adopted since the
early days of Encyclopædia Inflationaris to derive
reheating-consistent predictions. Ignoring it can indeed be
catastrophic. As an example, here are the reheating-consistent
predictions of one of the new model proposed <em>after</em> the Planck data
release. Not including reheating effects would imply selecting random
points in this mess…</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/opiparous/nsr_saiii3p_3.png" alt="saiii3p" /></p>

<hr />

<p>Let us note that in its new edition, the format of the paper has been
purposely kept similar to its original version. In particular, the
introduction (section 2) has been essentially left untouched in order
to keep track of our original motivations, and of the main
considerations that were discussed in the field at that time. We have
also not completed section 3 with a list of new analytical results
derived in the 46 new potentials, given that we think it has already
become clear that Encyclopædia Inflationaris is more than a review
indeed. At the time of this post, the opiparous edition is made public
only through <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1303.3787"><strong>arXiv:1303.3787v4</strong></a> with a full open access <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"><strong>CC BY-NC-SA
4.0</strong></a> license.</p>

<hr />

<p>Finally, about the benefit of a second edition, let us quote <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_le_Rond_d%27Alembert"><strong>Jean
Le Rond
d’Alembert</strong></a>
(in a letter to
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voltaire"><strong>Voltaire</strong></a>, June 23,
1766):</p>
<blockquote>

  <p>Quant à l’ouvrage, il est maigre, mais il est aisé de lui donner de l’embonpoint dans une seconde édition.</p>

</blockquote>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>These models may nonetheless come with different values for the parameters describing the potential, i.e. different priors in the framework of a Bayesian analysis. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We have released a new version of Encyclopædia Inflationaris and its associated public code ASPIC. This opiparous edition extends the original paper by 400 pages and features 46 new models of inflation that have been proposed in the last decade. Cosmic Inflation is ready to tackle the data challenges of tomorrow.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2023/04/03/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2023-04-03T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-04-03T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2023/04/03/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2023/04/03/seminar.html"><![CDATA[<p>The next cosmology seminar takes place on <strong>Wednesday 5th</strong> of
April, seminar <strong>room E349</strong> at <strong>2pm</strong>. Our guest speaker will be
<strong>Danièle Steer</strong> from APC (Paris, France).</p>

<hr />

<p>At 2pm, room E349, Danièle Steer (APC), will be talking about</p>

<h3 id="cosmology-and-distance-measurements-with-gravitational-wave-observations">Cosmology and distance measurements with gravitational wave observations</h3>

<p><em>In this talk I will outline the main different methods on the market
 for measuring cosmological parameters (including modified gravity
 parameters) with GWs, and the main sources of errors in these
 measurements. Then I will highlight the current results on
 cosmological parameters obtained with the O3 run of LIGO-Virgo, as
 well as give predictions for future expectations. Finally I will go
 into more technical details and explain an analytical approach to
 estimate distance errors with GW observations (from any number of
 ground based interferometers placed at different positions on
 earth).</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The next cosmology seminar takes place on Wednesday 5th of April, seminar room E349 at 2pm. Our guest speaker will be Danièle Steer from APC (Paris, France).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Big-Bang discussed by its inventor</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2023/01/19/GL.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Big-Bang discussed by its inventor" /><published>2023-01-19T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-19T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2023/01/19/GL</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2023/01/19/GL.html"><![CDATA[<p>A genuine filmed interview of <strong>Georges Lemaître</strong> from 1964
resurfaced. We can all listen to the inventor of the “Big-Bang”,
talking about his own theory, in French.</p>

<p>The live stream can be watched
<a href="https://vrtnws.be/p.OvM55PlWN"><strong>there</strong></a> while a transcripted
english translation has been published on the
<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.07198"><strong>arXiv</strong></a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A genuine filmed interview of Georges Lemaître from 1964 resurfaced. We can all listen to the inventor of the “Big-Bang”, talking about his own theory, in French.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/11/25/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2022-11-25T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-11-25T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/11/25/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/11/25/seminar.html"><![CDATA[<p>The next cosmology seminar takes place on <strong>Friday 2nd</strong> of
December, seminar <strong>room E349</strong> at <strong>2pm</strong>. Our guest speaker will be
<strong>Davide Dal Cin</strong> from SISSA (Trieste, Italy).</p>

<hr />

<p>At 2pm, room E349, Davide Dal Cin (SISSA), will be talking about</p>

<h3 id="planck-scale-physics-and-the-peccei-quinn-inflation-model">Planck-Scale Physics and the Peccei-Quinn inflation model</h3>

<p><em>The radial direction of the Peccei-Quinn field can drive cosmic
inflation, given a non-minimal coupling to gravity. This scenario has
been considered to be capable of explaining inflation, the strong
CP problem, and dark matter. We argue that Peccei-Quinn inflation
is extremely sensitive to higher-dimensional operators. Further
combining with the discussion on the axion quality required to solve
the strong CP problem, we examine the validity of this scenario. We
also show that a resonant amplification of the axion field is
unavoidable after Peccei–Quinn inflation.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The next cosmology seminar takes place on Friday 2nd of December, seminar room E349 at 2pm. Our guest speaker will be Davide Dal Cin from SISSA (Trieste, Italy).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mean-field approach to Random Apollonian Packing</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/11/20/2211.07509.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mean-field approach to Random Apollonian Packing" /><published>2022-11-20T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-11-20T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/11/20/2211.07509</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/11/20/2211.07509.html"><![CDATA[<p>Bubble nucleation is a phenomenon ubiquitous in physics, with
applications ranging from the geometry of tree crowns, the structure
of porous media and of sphere packing. Bubbles also find applications
in cosmology such as the characterization of cosmic voids in the large
scale structure and the signatures of cosmological phase
transitions. In a new preprint, <a href="/members/auclair.html"><strong>Pierre</strong></a>
proposes a new method to determine the fractal properties of the
so-called Random Apollonian Packing.</p>

<p>Random Apollonian Packing (RAP) is inspired by the better-known <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apollonian_gasket">Apollonian
Gasket</a>. In
mathematics, an Apollonian gasket is a fractal generated by starting
with a triple of circles, each tangent to the other two, and
successively filling in more circles, each tangent to another three.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2211.07509/gasket.svg" alt="gasket" title="Apollonian Gasket started from three equidistant cercles" /></p>

<p>In Ref. (missing reference), Pierre examines a
related mechanism in which \(d\)-dimensional spheres are randomly
seeded in space, one at a time, within a finite-sized volume, and
with the largest possible radius that avoids overlap.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2211.07509/packing-full.svg" alt="packing" title="One realization of a Random Apollonian Packing with the first 1000 spheres" /></p>

<p>The interest of the RAP mechanism is that it is thought to share
universal properties with more general dynamic mechanisms, such as the
ABK mechanism (named after Andrienko, Brilliantov and Krapivsky) in
which bubbles grow linearly with time.</p>

<p>Pierre has built a model to explain at which rate Random Apollonian Packings grow after the
insertion of one sphere after the other. The model’s prediction for
the fractal properties of RAP are consistent with numerical
simulations made in two, three and four dimensions.</p>

<p>If you want to explore a RAP in depth, feel free to zoom in that
<a href="https://curl.irmp.ucl.ac.be/~pierre/index.html"><strong>picture</strong></a>, it
contains more than a million spheres.</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Bubble nucleation is a phenomenon ubiquitous in physics, with applications ranging from the geometry of tree crowns, the structure of porous media and of sphere packing. Bubbles also find applications in cosmology such as the characterization of cosmic voids in the large scale structure and the signatures of cosmological phase transitions. In a new preprint, Pierre proposes a new method to determine the fractal properties of the so-called Random Apollonian Packing.]]></summary></entry></feed>