<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://curl.group/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://curl.group/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-12-19T15:45:21+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/</id><title type="html">CURL</title><subtitle>Research Group</subtitle><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><entry><title type="html">Post-doctoral opening in Cosmology</title><link href="https://curl.group/jobs/2018/12/19/PDR.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Post-doctoral opening in Cosmology" /><published>2018-12-19T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-12-19T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/jobs/2018/12/19/PDR</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/jobs/2018/12/19/PDR.html">&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce the opening of a &lt;strong&gt;post-doctoral position&lt;/strong&gt; in
Cosmology at CURL (Cosmology, Universe and Relativity at Louvain),
Louvain University (Belgium), starting fall 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applicants interested in early universe models, cosmic defects,
primordial black holes, cosmic inflation, as well as data analysis for
the future observational missions (CMB, GW, galaxy surveys, 21cm,
Euclid, LISA…) are encouraged to apply. Please notice that
applicants should have obtained their PhD no longer than 5 years
before the starting date of the fellowship, plus one year of allowance
for parenthood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appointment is available for up to three years, depending on results
and performance, and is supported by the Belgian National Fund for
Scientific Research (FNRS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of our current interests can be consulted on the CURL
website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://curl.group&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;curl.group&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letters of application (including a curriculum vitae, a list of
publications, a brief statement of research interests) and at least
two recommendation letters from senior scientists should be sent by
the 15th of February 2019 to &lt;strong&gt;christophe.ringeval@uclouvain.be&lt;/strong&gt; with
the subject containing the wordings &lt;strong&gt;[JOB19]&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postal mail applications can be addressed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Cosmology, Universe and Relativity at Louvain
Institute of Mathematics and Physics
Louvain University
2, Chemin du Cyclotron
1348 Louvain-la-Neuve
Belgium
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Jobs" /><summary type="html">We are happy to announce the opening of a post-doctoral position in Cosmology at CURL (Cosmology, Universe and Relativity at Louvain), Louvain University (Belgium), starting fall 2019.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">IRMP colloquium on crowd-sourcing optical follow-up searches</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2018/11/14/IRMP.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IRMP colloquium on crowd-sourcing optical follow-up searches" /><published>2018-11-14T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-11-14T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2018/11/14/IRMP</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2018/11/14/IRMP.html">&lt;p&gt;Some echos from Ref. &lt;a href=&quot;#boucher:2018xvk&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/news/2018/01/01/1801.04124.html&quot;&gt;this
post&lt;/a&gt;. Thursday,
2pm, room CYCL 01, C. Ringeval gives a talk for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://agenda.irmp.ucl.ac.be/event/3162/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IRMP
colloquium&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crowd-sourcing-galaxy-clusters-confirmation-with-non-professional-telescopes&quot;&gt;Crowd-sourcing galaxy clusters confirmation with non-professional telescopes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The new all sky and multi-wavelength astrophysical and cosmological
 surveys are, and will be, providing an unprecedented amount of
 information on a plethora of cosmic objects. Many of them are
 foregrounds for the original science goals and cannot received the
 same attention as the mission main objectives. Within the Planck
 satellite maps of our universe, a space telescope dedicated to the
 observation of the Cosmic Microwave Background, a few thousand of so
 far undetected galaxy clusters are letting very peculiar imprints
 through the so-called Sunyaev Zel’dovich effect. These cluster
 candidates have never been observed with optical telescopes and
 confirmation of their true nature requires a significant amount of
 professional telescope time.  In this talk, I will present a
 proof-of-concept of crowd-sourcing galaxy clusters optical
 confirmation with amateur astronomers. Using a non-professional
 telescope of 62cm provided by the Astroqueyras association in
 Saint-Véran (France), we have been able to confirm one of the Planck
 cluster candidate and to extract various of its properties, such as
 distance, redshift and mass. Although the exposure time required to
 image one cluster candidate is an order of magnitude larger than with
 a professional telescope, there are orders of magnitude more amateur
 astronomers than professionals thereby rendering the concept useful
 to many other surveys. They are the South Pole Telescope, the Atacama
 Cosmology Telescope, future X-ray spatial missions such as eRosita,
 and all of the searches for gravitational wave optical counterparts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">Some echos from Ref. [1] and this post. Thursday, 2pm, room CYCL 01, C. Ringeval gives a talk for the IRMP colloquium.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Georges Lemaître Chair 2018</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2018/11/06/GLChair.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Georges Lemaître Chair 2018" /><published>2018-11-06T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-11-06T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2018/11/06/GLChair</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2018/11/06/GLChair.html">&lt;p&gt;The “Chaire Georges Lemaître 2018” is taking place at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://uclouvain.be/en/research-institutes/irmp&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IRMP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; the week
of the 26th of November. &lt;strong&gt;Prof. Roberto Trotta&lt;/strong&gt; will be giving a
serie of lectures from Monday to Friday on “Astrostatistics in
Action”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/glchair/gl2018.png&quot; alt=&quot;glchair&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program consists in an Inaugural Lecture followed by a reception
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://agenda.irmp.ucl.ac.be/event/3164/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Registration here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;),
Monday at 16:15, CYCL01.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;if-you-dont-need-astrostatistics-you-have-done-the-wrong-experiment&quot;&gt;If You Don’t need (Astro)Statistics, You Have Done the Wrong Experiment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At the beginning of last century, the physicist and Nobel Prize
Winner Ernest Rutherford reportedly believed that “If your experiment
needs statistics, you ought to have done a better experiment”. If he
were alive today, he probably would not recognize the way cosmology
(the study of the Universe on its largest scale) has developed:
essentially all of the exciting discoveries in the last two decades
have relied on sophisticated statistical analyses of very large and
complex datasets. Today, advanced astrostatistical methods belong to
the toolbox of almost every cosmologist.  In this talk I will give an
overview of how cosmologists have established a “cosmological
concordance model” that explains extraordinarily well very accurate
observations ranging from the relic radiation from the Big Bang to the
distribution of galaxies in the sky in the modern Universe. The
emerging picture of a cosmos remains puzzling: 95% of the Universe is
constituted of unknown components, dark matter and dark energy. Our
understanding of the Universe is – already today – limited by our
statistical and computational methods. I will discuss how
astrostatistics will meet the challenges posed by upcoming extremely
large data sets and thereby be instrumental in answering some of the
most fundamental questions about the physical reality of the cosmos.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2 hours lectures start on Tuesday 10:00 am, room E-349, till
Friday. If you intend to follow one, or more, lectures, you &lt;strong&gt;MUST&lt;/strong&gt;
register below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://agenda.irmp.ucl.ac.be/event/3165/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REGISTRATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lecture-1-how-to-learn-from-experience-principle-of-bayesian-inference&quot;&gt;Lecture 1: How to Learn from Experience: Principle of Bayesian Inference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The problem of inference from noisy and/or partial data is ubiquitous
in science. It is particularly acute in observational disciplines,
like astrophysics and cosmology, where we don’t have the luxury of
being able to control our experiments.  I will introduce the
fundamental principles of Bayesian inference as a complete theory for
how to learn from experience, and contrast this approach with the more
traditional frequentist view of probability. I will also discuss
practical Bayesian methods and technology to determine posterior
distributions, including Markov Chain Monte Carlo and related sampling
schemes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lecture-2-shaving-theories-with-occams-razor-bayesian-model-comparison&quot;&gt;Lecture 2: Shaving Theories with Occam’s Razor: Bayesian Model Comparison&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Many of the questions in astroparticle physics, cosmology and
particle physics aim at establishing which theoretical model is the
best explanation for the available data.  Classically, theories can
only be falsified by ruling them out (the Popperian view). I will
demonstrate how the Bayesian model comparison approach is more
general, enabling physicists to correctly reward models that make
precise predictions that are then verified by experiment or
observation. I will contrast this with the hypothesis testing
paradigm, and discuss consequences for our understanding of what a
“significant result” means. I will illustrate analytical and numerical
methods for the implementation of Bayesian model comparison with
examples from cosmology and particle physics.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lecture-3-bayesian-hierarchical-models-and-applications-to-supernova-type-ia-cosmology&quot;&gt;Lecture 3: Bayesian Hierarchical Models and Applications to Supernova Type Ia Cosmology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to large and accurate measurements obtained in the last 2 decades, and to
sophisticated statistical analyses, cosmologists have established a “cosmological
concordance model” that reproduces well observations ranging from the relic radiation
from the Big Bang to the distribution of galaxies in the sky in the modern Universe. I will
review the observational and theoretical underpinnings of this so-called “Lambda-CDM”
concordance model of cosmology, which strongly points to the existence of both dark
matter and dark energy.
I will then focus on recent advances in supernova type Ia cosmology. Supernovae type Ia are
a type of stellar explosion that can be used as standard candles to measure extragalactic
distances, and have been instrumental in determining the accelerated expansion of the
Universe – a smoking gun observation for the existence of dark energy. I will present recent
results and a novel, powerful (Bayesian) statistical framework for interpreting the data,
including cosmological parameter inference, selection effects and classification in the
absence of spectroscopic data. I will discuss upcoming challenges for the field as the
quantity and quality of upcoming data sets increases.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lecture-4-applications-of-astrostatistics-to-dark-matter-phenomenology-and-beyond-the-standard-model-theories&quot;&gt;Lecture 4: Applications of Astrostatistics to Dark Matter Phenomenology and Beyond the Standard Model Theories&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The study of dark matter phenomenology and of underlying theoretical
models has advanced dramatically in recent years thanks to the
development of “global fits” ­ an approach to combine all available
data in a statistically convergent fit of Beyond the Standard Model
theoretical parameters. This approach now includes sophisticated
methods to simultaneously use direct detection, indirect detection and
collider data to constrain the parameter space for dark matter, and
map this onto the underlying theory parameters, e.g.  in
Supersymmetry.  I will describe the “global fits” approach and its
ability to deliver quantitative inference both from a Bayesian and a
frequentist (profile likelihood) point of view. I will review current
results in the field and associated challenges.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">The “Chaire Georges Lemaître 2018” is taking place at IRMP the week of the 26th of November. Prof. Roberto Trotta will be giving a serie of lectures from Monday to Friday on “Astrostatistics in Action”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Public conference series on Black Holes, Big-Bang and Universe</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/10/10/UDA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Public conference series on Black Holes, Big-Bang and Universe" /><published>2018-10-10T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-10T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/10/10/UDA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/10/10/UDA.html">&lt;p&gt;S. Clesse is giving a series of public lectures for the Université des
Aînés, the 10th, 17th and 24th of October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information there: &lt;a href=&quot;https://universitedesaines.be/fiche-formation.php?categorie=82&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UDA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">S. Clesse is giving a series of public lectures for the Université des Aînés, the 10th, 17th and 24th of October.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">L’univers avant le milliardième de seconde</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/10/08/UDA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="L'univers avant le milliardième de seconde" /><published>2018-10-08T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-08T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/10/08/UDA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/10/08/UDA.html">&lt;p&gt;Public conference by C. Ringeval on Cosmology and Cosmic Inflation for
the Université des Aînés, open to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information there: &lt;a href=&quot;https://universitedesaines.be/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UDA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/uda_091018.png&quot; alt=&quot;uda_poster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">Public conference by C. Ringeval on Cosmology and Cosmic Inflation for the Université des Aînés, open to everyone.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">La Cosmologie Moderne</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/09/21/CAAPC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="La Cosmologie Moderne" /><published>2018-09-21T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-21T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/09/21/CAAPC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/09/21/CAAPC.html">&lt;p&gt;For the equinox, S. Clesse gives a public lecture on The Big-Bang
model for the Cercle des Astronomes Amateurs de Charleroi. More
information there:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://caapc.be/calendrier%202011.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CAAPS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/cosmologie_Charleroi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;CAAPC_first_slide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">For the equinox, S. Clesse gives a public lecture on The Big-Bang model for the Cercle des Astronomes Amateurs de Charleroi. More information there:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Belgian Gravitational Waves meeting</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2018/09/12/BGW.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Belgian Gravitational Waves meeting" /><published>2018-09-12T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-12T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2018/09/12/BGW</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2018/09/12/BGW.html">&lt;p&gt;On Thursday 25th, we have the pleasure to host the Belgian
Gravitational Waves meeting. It starts at &lt;strong&gt;2pm&lt;/strong&gt;, seminar &lt;strong&gt;room
E349&lt;/strong&gt;. Our guest speakers are &lt;strong&gt;Stefan Antusch&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Giulia
Cusin&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fys.kuleuven.be/gwc/activities-folder/GWseminars&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GW meetings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 14:00, Stefan Antusch (Basel U.), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;oscillons-and-gravitational-waves-from-preheating-after-inflation&quot;&gt;Oscillons and gravitational waves from preheating after inflation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We discuss the preheating phase after inflation in particle physics
motivated models of the early universe. We show that the non-linear
dynamics after hilltop-type inflation models, where inflation can be
linked to a particle physics phase transition, can lead to the
formation of oscillons, comparatively long-lived and strong local
fluctuations of the inflaton field. Similar types of scalar field
potentials also appear in the KKLT scenario in string phenomenology,
and oscillons can form for the modulus field. We argue that when the
oscillons are asymmetric for a sufficiently long period, they can
generate a peak in the otherwise rather broad gravitational wave
spectrum produced during the earlier phases of preheating.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a coffee break, at 15:30, Giulia Cusin (Oxford U.) will talk about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;astrophysical-background-of-gravitational-waves-from-cosmology-to-a-new-era-of-precision-astrophysics&quot;&gt;Astrophysical background of gravitational waves: from cosmology to a new era of precision astrophysics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The astrophysical background of gravitational waves (AGWB) is made up
by the incoherent superposition of gravitational wave signals emitted
by a large number of resolved and unresolved astrophysical sources
from the onset of stellar activity until today, and that we collect at
our detectors. I present a theoretical framework to fully characterize
the AGWB in terms of energy density anisotropies and polarization and
I show the first numerical predictions for the angular power spectra
of anisotropies in different frequency bands and for
cross-correlations with electromagnetic observables such as weak
leaning and galaxy number counts. l then illustrate and discuss the
astrophysical implications of this study.  By properly modelling the
properties of the AGWB, it will be possible to extract for the first
time precise data on galactic and stellar physics and on astrophysical
processes of GW emission. In the same way as the discovery and study
of the cosmic microwave background has represented a turning point for
cosmology, the study of the AGWB will represent a true revolution for
astrophysics eventually leading to a new era of precision
astrophysics.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">On Thursday 25th, we have the pleasure to host the Belgian Gravitational Waves meeting. It starts at 2pm, seminar room E349. Our guest speakers are Stefan Antusch and Giulia Cusin.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interview for ScienceToday</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/09/05/ScienceToday.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview for ScienceToday" /><published>2018-09-05T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-05T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/09/05/ScienceToday</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/09/05/ScienceToday.html">&lt;p&gt;The publication of the Planck 2018 results is featured in the
ScienceToday UCL website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://uclouvain.be/fr/sciencetoday/actualites/l-heritage-de-planck.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L’héritage de Planck&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">The publication of the Planck 2018 results is featured in the ScienceToday UCL website.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The 2018 Planck results are public!</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2018/07/17/Planck2018.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 2018 Planck results are public!" /><published>2018-07-17T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-07-17T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2018/07/17/Planck2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2018/07/17/Planck2018.html">&lt;p&gt;Celebrating the anniversary of George Lemaître, the final 2018 release
of the Planck satellite measurements have been published today on the
ESA website and the arXiv. They currently provide the strongest
constraints on the Big-Bang model, and much more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All papers are there: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cosmos.esa.int/web/planck/publications#Planck2018&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planck 2018 results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first paper on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1807.06205&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;legacy of
Planck&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; provides a nice overview
of what Planck has been achieving since its launch in 2009!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">Celebrating the anniversary of George Lemaître, the final 2018 release of the Planck satellite measurements have been published today on the ESA website and the arXiv. They currently provide the strongest constraints on the Big-Bang model, and much more!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Two cosmology seminars in a row!</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2018/06/27/seminars.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two cosmology seminars in a row!" /><published>2018-06-27T14:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-27T14:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2018/06/27/seminars</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2018/06/27/seminars.html">&lt;p&gt;This Wednesday, we have not one but two cosmology seminars in a row!
We have the pleasure to receive &lt;strong&gt;Mateo Martinelli&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Alkistis Pourtsidou&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 13:00, Mateo Martinelli (Leiden U., Euclid), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;future-constraints-on-parametrized-modified-gravity-the-impact-of-non-linear-scales-and-of-theoretical-priors&quot;&gt;Future constraints on parametrized modified gravity: the impact of	non linear scales and of theoretical priors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this talk I will present forecasted constraints on
Modified Gravity using Galaxy Clustering and Weak Lensing
measurements. I will explore different possible phenomenological
parametrizations for Modified Gravity models, encoding the effects of
these modifications in two generic functions (η and μ) of time and
space which affect the Poisson equation and the so-called
gravitational slip. I will focus on forecasts for future surveys and I
will highlight the constraining power gained when including non linear
scales in the analysis using phenomenological prescription for the
modelling of these scales in the Modified Gravity framework.  I will
then discuss how it is possible to connect phenomenological
parameterizations to viable theories of modified gravity, imposing
theoretical conditions on the reconstructed functions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a coffee break, at 14:30, Alkistis Pourtsidou (Queen Mary U.,
SKA, Euclid) will talk about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cosmology-with-neutral-hydrogen-hi-intensity-mapping&quot;&gt;Cosmology with neutral hydrogen (HI) intensity mapping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I will introduce the innovative technique of HI intensity
mapping, which allows for precise cosmological measurements in the
radio wavelength. After talking about the current status of intensity
mapping measurements, I will focus on forthcoming surveys using
instruments like MeerKAT/SKA and CHIME to probe dark energy as well as
galaxy evolution. I will also present synergies between optical galaxy
and radio intensity mapping surveys in order to probe dark energy and
gravity, mitigate systematic effects, calibrate photometric redshifts,
and measure primordial non-gaussianity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">This Wednesday, we have not one but two cosmology seminars in a row! We have the pleasure to receive Mateo Martinelli and Alkistis Pourtsidou.</summary></entry></feed>