<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://curl.group/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://curl.group/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-04-04T17:53:58+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/feed.xml</id><title type="html">CURL</title><subtitle>Research Group</subtitle><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/04/04/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2022-04-04T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-04T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/04/04/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/04/04/seminar.html">&lt;p&gt;The next cosmology seminar takes place on &lt;strong&gt;Thursday 7th&lt;/strong&gt; of
April, seminar &lt;strong&gt;room E349&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;11am&lt;/strong&gt;. Our guest speaker will be
&lt;strong&gt;Fabien Lacasa&lt;/strong&gt; from the Institut d’Astrophysique Spatiale (Orsay,
France).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 11:00, room E349, Fabien Lacasa (IAS), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cosmology-with-the-cosmic-web-the-high-resolution-promise&quot;&gt;Cosmology with the cosmic web: the high resolution promise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The large scale structure of the Universe, the cosmic web, is a key
probe for late-time cosmology, and is indeed targeted by several of
the major observational efforts in the coming decades. However, its
analysis is hampered by the complex non-linear dynamics it undergoes
as structure grow. A lot of efforts has focused on the impact of
non-linearity on the observables, in particular the power
spectrum. However, the non-linearity also affects error bars, and thus
the information content, by generating non-Gaussian tails that induce
new covariance term. After sufficient introduction, I will present a
first exhaustive derivation of the covariance of the galaxy angular
power spectrum. The impact will then be presented for a baseline
cosmological analysis up to mildly non-linear scale, showing
decreasing returns. By contrast, I will finally show that there is a
large motivation to jump more boldly and push into the strongly
non-linear regime at high resolution.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">The next cosmology seminar takes place on Thursday 7th of April, seminar room E349 at 11am. Our guest speaker will be Fabien Lacasa from the Institut d’Astrophysique Spatiale (Orsay, France).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gravitational multifield dynamics on Higgs pre-inflation and preheating</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/03/08/2202.07604.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gravitational multifield dynamics on Higgs pre-inflation and preheating" /><published>2022-03-08T09:42:07+01:00</published><updated>2022-03-08T09:42:07+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/03/08/2202.07604</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/03/08/2202.07604.html">&lt;p&gt;Traditionally the problem of initial conditions for inflation has been
treated separately from studies of reheating. To allow for a
parametric-type reheating, the inflaton must be allowed to interact
with (or decay to) other fields, and, these interactions should be
present also during inhomogeneous preinflation. Could they prevent
cosmic inflation to start in the first place?  In a single-author
publication &lt;a href=&quot;/members/joana.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cristian&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; answers this question
for Higgs Inflation: once more, inflation always starts and passes the
challenge!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inflationary paradigm postulates an early phase of accelerated
expansion of the Universe. Such a period provides an explanation for
the observed large-scale homogeneity and flatness in the cosmos.
After the end of inflation, the universe would have gone through a
phase where the energy of the inflaton is transferred to Standard
Model particles, heating up the universe and leading to a bath of
ultra-relativistic particles behaving like radiation.  This phase is
known as reheating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally the problem of initial condition for inflation, i.e.,
knowing if inflation can start from highly inhomogeneous initial
conditions, has been treated separately from studies of
reheating. However, they are connected. To allow for the so-called
parametric-type reheating, through resonances occurring while the
system is oscillating at the bottom of the potential, the inflaton
must be microscopically coupled to other fields. So, again, one could
raise the question: shouldn’t these interactions be present also
during inhomogeneous preinflation? Do they prevent cosmic inflation
to start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a previous paper, see Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#joana:2020rxm&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, we have
studied the robustness of &lt;em&gt;single-field&lt;/em&gt; Higgs Inflation to
inhomogeneous initial conditions of all sizes. We have paid attention
to include the gravitational dynamics of the system, showing the possible
formation of pre-inflationary black holes, as well as the generation
of shear/tensor modes in the metric. In short, we have showed that
these gravitational dynamics can only delay the beginning of inflation, but
never prevent it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#joana:2022uwc&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/members/joana.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cristian&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
expands the previous settings by adding an extra field into the Higgs
Inflation model. This field is coupled such that it allows for a
reheating of the Universe. Reheating is actually successful for a
range of the field-field interaction strength, which is numerically
explored in full General Relativity simulations. Then the same model
is confronted to various preinflationary inhomogeneous settings and the
full gravitational and scalar-field dynamics are investigated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure below shows the preheating resonances for the auxiliary
field (left panel). Structure formation occurs \(2\)-\(3\) e-folds
after the end of inflation (right panel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2202.07604/Reh_01.png&quot; alt=&quot;reh&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the exact same model during the inhomogeneous multi-field
preinflationary epochs, we confirm that the Higgs non-minimal coupling
to gravity acts as a stabilizer as it &lt;em&gt;washes out&lt;/em&gt; the energy
contribution of the other minimally coupled matter/scalar-field
sectors. In Ref &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#joana:2022uwc&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, it is shown that this occurs
naturally when one canonically normalizes the fields in the Einstein
frame. This effect generalizes the dynamics of inhomogeneous
extra-matter components, making them sub-dominant in comparison to the
inflaton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2202.07604/mf_preinf.png&quot; alt=&quot;preinf&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above figure illustrates the gravitational and scalar-field
dynamics during pre-inflation. Two simulations are shown, one with
super-Hubble initial conditions (left) and another with sub-Hubble
size inhomogeneities (right).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, these investigations further confirm the robustness of
Higgs Inflation to multi-field inhomogeneous initial conditions, while
putting in evidence the formation of complex structures during the
reheating. The possible production of compact objects during the
reheating, such as primordial black holes, will be investigated in
future works.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">Traditionally the problem of initial conditions for inflation has been treated separately from studies of reheating. To allow for a parametric-type reheating, the inflaton must be allowed to interact with (or decay to) other fields, and, these interactions should be present also during inhomogeneous preinflation. Could they prevent cosmic inflation to start in the first place? In a single-author publication Cristian answers this question for Higgs Inflation: once more, inflation always starts and passes the challenge!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2021/11/22/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2021-11-22T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-11-22T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2021/11/22/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2021/11/22/seminar.html">&lt;p&gt;Our next cosmology seminar takes place on &lt;strong&gt;Wednesday 1st&lt;/strong&gt; of December,
seminar &lt;strong&gt;room E349&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;2pm&lt;/strong&gt;. The speaker is &lt;strong&gt;Maxence Corman&lt;/strong&gt;
from the Perimeter Institute (Waterloo, Canada).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 14:00, room E349, Maxence Corman (PI), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;evolving-black-holes-in-a-nonsingular-bouncing-universe&quot;&gt;Evolving black holes in a nonsingular bouncing universe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One of the main unanswered questions of theoretical cosmology is
whether the universe emerged from a big bang followed by a period of
inflation or whether it had no beginning at all and bounced from a
period of slow contraction to the current expanding phase.  It has
been shown recently that it is possible for the universe to undergo a
nonsingular bounce at energies well below the Planck scale such that
the entire evolution can be treated classically. It is however still
unclear how to treat the passage of any pre-existing black holes
through the bounce to the expanding phase.  In this talk, we use
numerical techniques to consider the classical evolution of a black
hole in a non-singular universe driven by a ``ghost’’ scalar field. We
find that at least for small enough black holes, the black hole passes
through the bounce freely, albeit losing energy in the process.
Pushing this further, we also show that if the Hubble patch during
contraction shrinks to a size comparable or smaller than the radius of
the black hole this gives rise to interesting dynamics such as
disappearing and re-emerging horizons.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">Our next cosmology seminar takes place on Wednesday 1st of December, seminar room E349 at 2pm. The speaker is Maxence Corman from the Perimeter Institute (Waterloo, Canada).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2021/11/15/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2021-11-15T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-11-15T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2021/11/15/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2021/11/15/seminar.html">&lt;p&gt;Our next cosmology seminar takes place on &lt;strong&gt;Friday 19th&lt;/strong&gt; of November,
seminar &lt;strong&gt;room E349&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;2pm&lt;/strong&gt;. The speaker is &lt;strong&gt;Danilo Artigas&lt;/strong&gt;
from the Institut d’Astrophysique Spatiale (Paris, France) and Quantum
Cosmos Lab (Cracow, Poland).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 14:00, room E349, Danilo Artigas (IAS), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hamiltonian-formalism-for-cosmological-perturbations-the-separate-universe-approach&quot;&gt;Hamiltonian formalism for cosmological perturbations: the separate-universe approach&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In order to describe inhomogeneities and anisotropies in the Universe,
one generally considers a Friedmann-Lemaître-Robertson-Walker
background and introduces perturbations on top of it. Such a method is
commonly used in Lagrangian formalism and is fundamental for example
in order to describe the formation of large-scale structures. On the
other hand, the so-called “separate-universe” approach aims to provide
an effective description of cosmological perturbations at large
scales. In this talk, we will formulate the perturbation theory and
the separate universe approach in the Hamiltonian language. We will
then compare both frameworks to determine the domain of validity of
the separate universe. As expected, both match at large scales since
anisotropic degrees of freedom decouple from homogeneous ones. We’ll
finish discussing the gauge matching between both approaches and the
construction of their gauge-invariant quantities.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">Our next cosmology seminar takes place on Friday 19th of November, seminar room E349 at 2pm. The speaker is Danilo Artigas from the Institut d’Astrophysique Spatiale (Paris, France) and Quantum Cosmos Lab (Cracow, Poland).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">~~Post-doctoral opening in Cosmology~~</title><link href="https://curl.group/jobs/2021/10/22/IISN.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="~~Post-doctoral opening in Cosmology~~" /><published>2021-10-22T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-22T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/jobs/2021/10/22/IISN</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/jobs/2021/10/22/IISN.html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://uclouvain.be/en/research-institutes/irmp&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Institute of Mathematics and
Physics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is
openening a post-doctoral research position in the field of Cosmology
starting fall 2022 to work in collaboration with Prof. M. Drewes
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://cp3.phys.ucl.ac.be&quot;&gt;CP3&lt;/a&gt;) and Prof. Ch. Ringeval
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://curl.irmp.ucl.ac.be&quot;&gt;CURL&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applicants interested in early universe cosmology, such as cosmic
inflation, reheating, connection with particle physics as well as
future cosmological observations (CMB-S4, Euclid, LiteBird, LISA…),
are particularly encouraged to apply. Please notice that applicants
should have obtained their PhD no longer than 5 years before the
starting date of the fellowship, plus one year of allowance for
parenthood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letters of application (including a curriculum vitae, a list of
publications, a brief statement of research interests) and at least
two recommendation letters from senior scientists should be submitted
on-line, by the 15th of December 2021, at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cp3.irmp.ucl.ac.be/jobs/74&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;https://cp3.irmp.ucl.ac.be/jobs/74&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, or postal applications, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;christophe.ringeval@uclouvain.be
Cosmology, Universe and Relativity at Louvain
Institute of Mathematics and Physics
Louvain University
2, Chemin du Cyclotron
1348 Louvain-la-Neuve
Belgium
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of our current interests can be consulted on the CURL
website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://curl.group&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;curl.group&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Jobs" /><summary type="html">The Institute of Mathematics and Physics is openening a post-doctoral research position in the field of Cosmology starting fall 2022 to work in collaboration with Prof. M. Drewes (CP3) and Prof. Ch. Ringeval (CURL).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From quantum fluctuations to galaxies</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2021/10/15/CAAPC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From quantum fluctuations to galaxies" /><published>2021-10-15T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-15T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2021/10/15/CAAPC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2021/10/15/CAAPC.html">&lt;p&gt;C. Ringeval gives a public lecture on Cosmic Inflation for the Cercle
des Astronomes Amateurs de Charleroi (starts at 7:45pm). More information at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://caapc.be/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CAAPC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;linflation-cosmique-du-vide-quantique-aux-galaxies&quot;&gt;L’Inflation Cosmique: du vide quantique aux galaxies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Les mesures astronomiques et cosmologiques de ce début de siècle ont
permis de déterminer avec une précision redoutable la nature et les
abondances de toutes les formes d’énergie présentes dans l’Univers.
Elles ont, une fois de plus, donné raison au modèle du Big-Bang de
George Lemaître. Celui-ci décrit donc, avec précision, notre Univers
sur des distances allant jusqu’à la dizaine de gigaparsecs et nous
permet de comprendre son histoire dès la seconde après la singularité
initiale.  Cependant, nous verrons comment ces mesures posent aussi
des questions surprenantes sur l’évolution de l’Univers dans son
premier milliardième de seconde d’existence. Nous expliquerons
pourquoi la plus plausible des réponses est l’Inflation
Cosmique. Celle-ci nous dit que l’Univers eut été en accélération
quasi-exponentielle, dénué de toute de matière et lumière, gorgé de
fluctuations quantiques et d’ondes gravitationnelles : les embryons
des galaxies d’aujourd’hui.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/inflation_Charleroi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;CAAPC_first_slide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">C. Ringeval gives a public lecture on Cosmic Inflation for the Cercle des Astronomes Amateurs de Charleroi (starts at 7:45pm). More information at CAAPC.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Belgian Cosmo Meeting</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2021/10/05/BCosmo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Belgian Cosmo Meeting" /><published>2021-10-05T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-05T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2021/10/05/BCosmo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2021/10/05/BCosmo.html">&lt;p&gt;We hold an informal meeting during which new comers working in
Cosmology will present their work and research topics. This takes
place Wednesday 6th of October, seminar room E349 from 2pm to 6pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program starts at 14:00 with Albert Escrivà (ULB, Phys. Th.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;formation-of-primordial-black-holes&quot;&gt;Formation of Primordial Black Holes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Primordial Black Holes (PBHs) could have been formed in the very
 early universe due to the collapse of large curvature fluctuations
 after inflation. PBHs are nowadays one of the most attractive and
 fascinating research areas in cosmology for their possible
 theoretical and observational implications. In this talk, I will
 review the physical process of PBH formation, and the numerical
 tools used to simulate them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 14:45, Pierre Auclair (UCLouvain, CURL) will talk about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;population-of-cosmic-strings-and-gravitational-waves&quot;&gt;Population of cosmic strings and gravitational waves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cosmic strings are one-dimensional topological defects that could be
 formed during phase transitions in the primordial Universe. If
 formed, these relics would be markers of the upheavals of our early
 universe. During this talk, we will discuss about the evolution of
 the cosmic string network, in particular the density of loops and
 their gravitational wave emission. We will then make the connection
 with the future space-based LISA mission, and the results from
 LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA. If time permits, we will also show that the
 presence of cosmic strings may also affect other types of
 observables, such as the dark matter content of the Universe and the
 diffuse gamma-ray background.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a break, at 16:00, Isabel Oldengott (UCLouvain, CP3) will be
talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;local-relic-neutrino-density-with-kinetic-field-theory&quot;&gt;Local relic neutrino density with kinetic field theory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kinetic field theory (KFT) is a statistical field theory for an
 ensemble of classical particles. It has quite recently been applied
 to large scale structure formation, showing a remarkable agreement to
 the results from N-body simulations. I am currently working on its
 application on the computation of the local relic neutrino density
 and will give a short review on the current status of the project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">We hold an informal meeting during which new comers working in Cosmology will present their work and research topics. This takes place Wednesday 6th of October, seminar room E349 from 2pm to 6pm.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interferences in the Stochastic Gravitational Wave Background</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2021/05/06/2104.14231.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interferences in the Stochastic Gravitational Wave Background" /><published>2021-05-06T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-06T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2021/05/06/2104.14231</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2021/05/06/2104.14231.html">&lt;p&gt;Some cosmological sources of gravitational waves, such as cosmic
strings, are everywhere present and incessantly emitting. Their past
and present contribution can mix together to create some fine structure in
the stochastic gravitational wave background today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/members/dacunha.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disrael&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;/members/chris.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christophe&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; have calculated in Ref.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#dacunha:2021wyy&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; the all-length scales unequal-time strain power
spectrum \(\mathcal{P}_h\) and the energy density parameter
\(\Omega_{\mathrm{GW}}\) of gravitational waves generated by
various scaling sources. For extinct and smooth enough sources, they find that both quantities
have an oscillatory fine structure, represented as black dotted curve in the following
figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021.14231/singular_Ph_radinmat.png&quot; alt=&quot;csSmat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021.14231/singular_OmegaGW_mat.png&quot; alt=&quot;csEmat&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of that, singular and never extinct sources, such as cosmic
strings, can create interferences and their spectra exhibit a
different fine structure. They are represented as red curves in the
figures. For instance, long cosmic strings in the matter era are
expected to have a rescaled strain spectrum \(k^2
\mathcal{P}_h^{\mathrm{mat}}\) oscillating around a scale invariant
plateau (blue curve above), which is quite different from the one
associated with extinct and smooth sources. It also deviates
significantly from \(\Omega_{\mathrm{GW}}^{\mathrm{mat}}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the fine structure of the stochastic gravitational wave
background be measured?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">Some cosmological sources of gravitational waves, such as cosmic strings, are everywhere present and incessantly emitting. Their past and present contribution can mix together to create some fine structure in the stochastic gravitational wave background today.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A wibbly-wobbly timey-wimey path to salvation</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2020/12/10/2011.12190.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A wibbly-wobbly timey-wimey path to salvation" /><published>2020-12-10T09:42:07+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-10T09:42:07+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2020/12/10/2011.12190</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2020/12/10/2011.12190.html">&lt;p&gt;In a recent preprint, &lt;a href=&quot;/members/joana.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cristian&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;/members/clesse.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sébastien&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; show the robustness of
Starobinsky and Higgs inflation to inhomogeneous initial conditions of
all sizes. They have performed full numerical relativity simulations
with strong inhomogeneous initial field and velocities. After
some “wibbly-wobbly timey-wimey” evolution, the system relaxes
towards… &lt;strong&gt;Cosmic Inflation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their results are presented in Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#joana:2020rxm&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. Simulations show that sub-Hubble, as well as Hubble-sized, fluctuations
generically lead to inflation after an oscillatory phase between
gradient and kinetic energies. The following figure shows the
evolution of the equation of state for sub-Hubble (top), and
super-Hubble (bottom) inhomogeneous initial conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2011.12190/EoS.png&quot; alt=&quot;eos&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst Hubble-sized fluctuations are able to form large
pre-inflationary black holes, their horizons end up being always
sub-Hubble and this allows for inflation to take place in the
neighbourhood of the black hole horizon. These results could even
suggest that the formation of large pre-inflationary black holes can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catalysis&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;catalize&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; the onset of
inflation. They trap gradient energies and therefore smooth the field
and metric in the surrounding regions. An equatorial slice of a black
hole forming is represented below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2011.12190/BH_slc.png&quot; alt=&quot;bh&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradoxically, when inhomogeneities escape the formation of black
holes, the dynamics becomes the richest. On sub-Hubble scales, the
non-linear dynamics of the deeply inhomogeneous scalar field sources
metric backreactions in the form of shear and tensor modes. These
modes are found to decay slower than the energy density of the field
and can potentially dominate the energy content of the Universe for a
while. However, when this occurs, the beginning of inflation is simply
delayed but never prevented. The next figure represents a snapshot of
the gravitational modes “energy” produced in the sub-Hubble dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2011.12190/ECM_slc.png&quot; alt=&quot;preinf&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysis further supports the robustness of inflation to any size
of inhomogeneity, in the field, velocity or equation-of-state. At
large scalar field values, the pre-inflation dynamics only marginally
depends on the field potential and it is expected that such behaviour
is universal and it applies to any inflation potential of
plateau-type, as the ones favoured by the CMB observations after
Planck.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">In a recent preprint, Cristian and Sébastien show the robustness of Starobinsky and Higgs inflation to inhomogeneous initial conditions of all sizes. They have performed full numerical relativity simulations with strong inhomogeneous initial field and velocities. After some “wibbly-wobbly timey-wimey” evolution, the system relaxes towards… Cosmic Inflation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">~~Post-doctoral opening in Virgo/LIGO data analysis for the SGWB~~</title><link href="https://curl.group/jobs/2020/11/25/ARC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="~~Post-doctoral opening in Virgo/LIGO data analysis for the SGWB~~" /><published>2020-11-25T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-25T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/jobs/2020/11/25/ARC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/jobs/2020/11/25/ARC.html">&lt;p&gt;The Virgo gravitational wave group at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://uclouvain.be/en/research-institutes/irmp&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Institute of Mathematics
and Physics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, is
searching for an senior post-doctoral researcher to take a leading
role in the data analysis carried out within the LIGO and Virgo
searches for a Stochastic Gravitational Wave Background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deadline is the 10th of January 2021, more information and online
applications here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cp3.irmp.ucl.ac.be/jobs/65&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;https://cp3.irmp.ucl.ac.be/jobs/65&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Jobs" /><summary type="html">The Virgo gravitational wave group at the Institute of Mathematics and Physics, is searching for an senior post-doctoral researcher to take a leading role in the data analysis carried out within the LIGO and Virgo searches for a Stochastic Gravitational Wave Background.</summary></entry></feed>