<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://curl.group/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://curl.group/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-05-10T16:33:09+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/feed.xml</id><title type="html">CURL</title><subtitle>Research Group</subtitle><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><entry><title type="html">The opiparous edition of Encyclopædia Inflationaris</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2023/05/08/EI.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The opiparous edition of Encyclopædia Inflationaris" /><published>2023-05-08T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-05-08T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2023/05/08/EI</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2023/05/08/EI.html"><![CDATA[<p>We have released a new version of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1303.3787"><strong>Encyclopædia
Inflationaris</strong></a> and its associated
public code
<a href="https://github.com/cosmicinflation/aspic"><strong>ASPIC</strong></a>. This opiparous
edition extends the original paper by 400 pages and features 46 new
models of inflation that have been proposed in the last decade. Cosmic
Inflation is ready to tackle the data challenges of tomorrow.</p>

<p>The first edition of <strong>Encyclopædia Inflationaris</strong> was published in
Ref. <a class="citation" href="#martin:2014vha">[1]</a> and authored by <a href="https://inspirehep.net/q=a%20Jerome.Martin.1"><strong>Jérôme
Martin</strong></a>,
<a href="/members/chris.html"><strong>Christophe</strong></a> and <a href="https://www.lpens.ens.psl.eu/vincent-vennin/?lang=en"><strong>Vincent
Vennin</strong></a>. It
was built upon the slow-roll models of inflation proposed prior to
2013, the year of the first
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planck_(spacecraft)"><strong>Planck</strong></a> data
release. It contains accurate reheating-consistent slow-roll
calculations of the background universe and of the expected scalar and
tensor perturbations for all these models. Although it is now often
seen as a review, it is a genuine paper as it goes beyond the mere
gathering of known results. Indeed, a fair fraction of these models
had been studied only under rough approximations, which were not
matching the accuracy needed by the Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB)
data. The ambition of the project was, and still is, to provide an
(almost) exact treatment of single-field inflationary models using
only the slow-roll approximation while incorporating the kinematic
effects of reheating.</p>

<p>All these results are also incorporated in a public runtime library,
<strong>ASPIC</strong> <a class="citation" href="#aspic">[2]</a>, which has been used in a number of
subsequent works. For instance, Bayesian model comparison using the
Planck CMB data has been presented in Refs. <a class="citation" href="#martin:2013nzq">[3]</a>
and <a class="citation" href="#martin:2014rqa">[4]</a> while the constraints derived on the
reheating epoch have been separately presented in Refs. <a class="citation" href="#martin:2014nya">[5]</a> and <a class="citation" href="#martin:2016oyk">[6]</a>.</p>

<hr />

<p>Ten years later Cosmic Inflation remains the most favoured scenario
of the early universe <a class="citation" href="#chowdhury:2019otk">[7]</a> but several
developments have called for the release of a new edition:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>First, at the theoretical level, new models have been proposed. Some
of them boil down to one of the functional forms of the inflationary
potentials already encoded in ASPIC, in which case they have been
added in the relevant sections<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Some other models give rise to
new inflationary potentials, and therefore constitute new sections
of Encyclopædia Inflationaris, as well as new entries in the ASPIC
library. There are 24 such new potential functions in the new
edition (here ordered alphabetically): <strong>Axion Hilltop Inflation</strong>
(AHI), <strong>Cubicly Corrected Starobinsky Inflation</strong> (CCSI),<strong>Double
Exponential Inflation</strong> (DEI), <strong>Dual Inflation</strong> (DI), <strong>Fibre
Inflation</strong> (FI), Generalized Double Well Inflation (GDWI),
Hyperbolic Inflation (HBI), <strong>Hybrid Natural Inflation</strong> (HNI),
<strong>Non-Renormalizable Corrected Loop Inflation</strong> (NCLI),
<strong>N-Formalism Inflation</strong> (NFI), <strong>Non-Minimal Large Field
Inflation</strong> (NMLFI), <strong>Pure Arctan Inflation</strong> (PAI), <strong>Radiatively
Corrected Inflection Point Inflation</strong> (RCIPI), <strong>Radiatively
Corrected Large Field Inflation</strong> (RCLFI), <strong>String Axion Inflation
I</strong> (SAII), <strong>String Axion Inflation II (SAIII), Super-conformal
Alpha Attractor A Inflation</strong> (SAAI), <strong>T-Model Inflation</strong> (TMI),
<strong>Super-conformal Alpha Attractor B Inflation</strong> (SABI),
<strong>Super-conformal Alpha Attractor T Inflation</strong> (SATI), <strong>Symmetry
Breaking Kähler Inflation</strong> (SBKI), <strong>S-Dual Inflation</strong> (SDI),
<strong>Smeared Higgs Inflation</strong> (SHI), <strong>Mukhanov Inflation</strong>
(VFMI). The inclusion of these models allows the new edition to
provide an up-to-date landscape of all single-field slow-roll
inflationary models, bringing the number of models included in the
<strong>ASPIC</strong> library to 118.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Second, at the observational level, the first edition compared the
predictions of single-field models with the early release of the
Planck 2013 data. Since then, additional data has been collected,
and the second edition features second-order slow-roll constraints
from the full <a href="https://pla.esac.esa.int"><strong>Planck Legacy +
Bicep-Keck</strong></a> data combination. The
Bayesian evidence of all models has also been re-computed with the
new data set, and the results will be presented in a separate
publication.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Third, as the accuracy of the recent data releases has kept
improving, several projects are on their way that should deliver
even more accurate cosmological data in the years to come. In
particular, let us mention ground-based experiments that are
currently operating such as <a href="http://bicepkeck.org/"><strong>BICEP3 &amp; Keck
array</strong></a> and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Pole_Telescope"><strong>SPT</strong></a> in
Antarctica,
<a href="https://research.iac.es/proyecto/quijote/pages/en/home.php"><strong>QUIJOTE</strong></a>
in the Canary islands, and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmology_Large_Angular_Scale_Surveyor"><strong>CLASS</strong></a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atacama_Cosmology_Telescope"><strong>ACT</strong></a>
and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/POLARBEAR"><strong>Polarbear</strong></a> in the
Atacama desert. They have been very recently joined by
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qubic_experiment"><strong>QUBIC</strong></a>. In
space, the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euclid_(spacecraft)"><strong>Euclid</strong></a>
satellite is soon to be launched and will provide unprecedented
measurements on the matter power spectrum, down to very small
scales. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LiteBIRD"><strong>LiteBIRD</strong></a>
satellite is planned to be launched in 2028 and should allow us to
further constrain the \(B\)-mode signal in the polarisation of the
CMB. These prospects of ever increasing precision confirm the
relevance of the original Encyclopædia Inflationaris and ASPIC
projects, namely the need for accurate predictions on a
model-to-model basis. For this reason, we have continued to pay
special attention to solve the inflationary dynamics exactly,
without any other approximations than those contained in the
slow-roll framework. This one has indeed been shown to be
sufficiently accurate for the Planck CMB data <a class="citation" href="#ringeval:2013lea">[8]</a> and can be extended to arbitrary precision if
needed <a class="citation" href="#auclair:2022yxs">[9]</a>. On the contrary, as discussed in
Ref. <a class="citation" href="#martin:2016iqo">[10]</a> other commonly-employed
approximations are now too imprecise to allow for a fair comparison
with the data.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>Some of the new models are compatible with the present data, as one
could have expected, but this statement is <strong>strongly</strong> reheating
dependent. This can be illustrated by the following figure. It shows
their predictions, namely spectral index \(n_\mathrm{S}\) and
tensor-to-scalar ratio \(r\) as a function of the reheating energy
scale \(E_{\mathrm{reh}}\) (assuming a matter-like reheating for
illustration purposes). The contours are the \(68\%\) and \(95\%\)
confidence intervals associated with the successive Planck data
releases since 2013.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/opiparous/nslogr_plc3_bkppol.png"><img src="/assets/images/opiparous/nslogr_plc3_bkppol.png" alt="nslogr" title="Spectral index and tensor-to-scalar ratio" /></a></p>

<p>As this figure shows, getting reheating-consistent predictions has
never been so crucial. The reheating expansion history determines the
part of the inflationary potential being probed by cosmological
measurements, it can now substantially affect the preference shown by
the data for a given model (in technical terms, the Bayesian
evidence). This is one of the reasons why, in the opirarous edition,
the <strong>Starobinsky model</strong> (SI) and <strong>Higgs Inflation</strong> (HI) are now
treated as distinct models, since they come with different reheating
histories. Moreover, even though they are often treated as sharing the
same potential, this is only correct at leading order in an expansion
with respect to the inverse of the non-minimal coupling of the
field. Differences arise at next-to-leading order that we now account
for in an exact manner.</p>

<p>The previous figure certainly confirms the strategy adopted since the
early days of Encyclopædia Inflationaris to derive
reheating-consistent predictions. Ignoring it can indeed be
catastrophic. As an example, here are the reheating-consistent
predictions of one of the new model proposed <em>after</em> the Planck data
release. Not including reheating effects would imply selecting random
points in this mess…</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/opiparous/nsr_saiii3p_3.png" alt="saiii3p" /></p>

<hr />

<p>Let us note that in its new edition, the format of the paper has been
purposely kept similar to its original version. In particular, the
introduction (section 2) has been essentially left untouched in order
to keep track of our original motivations, and of the main
considerations that were discussed in the field at that time. We have
also not completed section 3 with a list of new analytical results
derived in the 46 new potentials, given that we think it has already
become clear that Encyclopædia Inflationaris is more than a review
indeed. At the time of this post, the opiparous edition is made public
only through <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1303.3787"><strong>arXiv:1303.3787v4</strong></a> with a full open access <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"><strong>CC BY-NC-SA
4.0</strong></a> license.</p>

<hr />

<p>Finally, about the benefit of a second edition, let us quote <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_le_Rond_d%27Alembert"><strong>Jean
Le Rond
d’Alembert</strong></a>
(in a letter to
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voltaire"><strong>Voltaire</strong></a>, June 23,
1766):</p>
<blockquote>

  <p>Quant à l’ouvrage, il est maigre, mais il est aisé de lui donner de l’embonpoint dans une seconde édition.</p>

</blockquote>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>These models may nonetheless come with different values for the parameters describing the potential, i.e. different priors in the framework of a Bayesian analysis. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We have released a new version of Encyclopædia Inflationaris and its associated public code ASPIC. This opiparous edition extends the original paper by 400 pages and features 46 new models of inflation that have been proposed in the last decade. Cosmic Inflation is ready to tackle the data challenges of tomorrow.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2023/04/03/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2023-04-03T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-04-03T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2023/04/03/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2023/04/03/seminar.html"><![CDATA[<p>The next cosmology seminar takes place on <strong>Wednesday 5th</strong> of
April, seminar <strong>room E349</strong> at <strong>2pm</strong>. Our guest speaker will be
<strong>Danièle Steer</strong> from APC (Paris, France).</p>

<hr />

<p>At 2pm, room E349, Danièle Steer (APC), will be talking about</p>

<h3 id="cosmology-and-distance-measurements-with-gravitational-wave-observations">Cosmology and distance measurements with gravitational wave observations</h3>

<p><em>In this talk I will outline the main different methods on the market
 for measuring cosmological parameters (including modified gravity
 parameters) with GWs, and the main sources of errors in these
 measurements. Then I will highlight the current results on
 cosmological parameters obtained with the O3 run of LIGO-Virgo, as
 well as give predictions for future expectations. Finally I will go
 into more technical details and explain an analytical approach to
 estimate distance errors with GW observations (from any number of
 ground based interferometers placed at different positions on
 earth).</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The next cosmology seminar takes place on Wednesday 5th of April, seminar room E349 at 2pm. Our guest speaker will be Danièle Steer from APC (Paris, France).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Big-Bang discussed by its inventor</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2023/01/19/GL.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Big-Bang discussed by its inventor" /><published>2023-01-19T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-19T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2023/01/19/GL</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2023/01/19/GL.html"><![CDATA[<p>A genuine filmed interview of <strong>Georges Lemaître</strong> from 1964
resurfaced. We can all listen to the inventor of the “Big-Bang”,
talking about his own theory, in French.</p>

<p>The live stream can be watched
<a href="https://vrtnws.be/p.OvM55PlWN"><strong>there</strong></a> while a transcripted
english translation has been published on the
<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.07198"><strong>arXiv</strong></a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A genuine filmed interview of Georges Lemaître from 1964 resurfaced. We can all listen to the inventor of the “Big-Bang”, talking about his own theory, in French.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/11/25/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2022-11-25T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-11-25T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/11/25/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/11/25/seminar.html"><![CDATA[<p>The next cosmology seminar takes place on <strong>Friday 2nd</strong> of
December, seminar <strong>room E349</strong> at <strong>2pm</strong>. Our guest speaker will be
<strong>Davide Dal Cin</strong> from SISSA (Trieste, Italy).</p>

<hr />

<p>At 2pm, room E349, Davide Dal Cin (SISSA), will be talking about</p>

<h3 id="planck-scale-physics-and-the-peccei-quinn-inflation-model">Planck-Scale Physics and the Peccei-Quinn inflation model</h3>

<p><em>The radial direction of the Peccei-Quinn field can drive cosmic
inflation, given a non-minimal coupling to gravity. This scenario has
been considered to be capable of explaining inflation, the strong
CP problem, and dark matter. We argue that Peccei-Quinn inflation
is extremely sensitive to higher-dimensional operators. Further
combining with the discussion on the axion quality required to solve
the strong CP problem, we examine the validity of this scenario. We
also show that a resonant amplification of the axion field is
unavoidable after Peccei–Quinn inflation.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The next cosmology seminar takes place on Friday 2nd of December, seminar room E349 at 2pm. Our guest speaker will be Davide Dal Cin from SISSA (Trieste, Italy).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mean-field approach to Random Apollonian Packing</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/11/20/2211.07509.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mean-field approach to Random Apollonian Packing" /><published>2022-11-20T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-11-20T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/11/20/2211.07509</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/11/20/2211.07509.html"><![CDATA[<p>Bubble nucleation is a phenomenon ubiquitous in physics, with
applications ranging from the geometry of tree crowns, the structure
of porous media and of sphere packing. Bubbles also find applications
in cosmology such as the characterization of cosmic voids in the large
scale structure and the signatures of cosmological phase
transitions. In a new preprint, <a href="/members/auclair.html"><strong>Pierre</strong></a>
proposes a new method to determine the fractal properties of the
so-called Random Apollonian Packing.</p>

<p>Random Apollonian Packing (RAP) is inspired by the better-known <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apollonian_gasket">Apollonian
Gasket</a>. In
mathematics, an Apollonian gasket is a fractal generated by starting
with a triple of circles, each tangent to the other two, and
successively filling in more circles, each tangent to another three.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2211.07509/gasket.svg" alt="gasket" title="Apollonian Gasket started from three equidistant cercles" /></p>

<p>In Ref. (missing reference), Pierre examines a
related mechanism in which \(d\)-dimensional spheres are randomly
seeded in space, one at a time, within a finite-sized volume, and
with the largest possible radius that avoids overlap.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2211.07509/packing-full.svg" alt="packing" title="One realization of a Random Apollonian Packing with the first 1000 spheres" /></p>

<p>The interest of the RAP mechanism is that it is thought to share
universal properties with more general dynamic mechanisms, such as the
ABK mechanism (named after Andrienko, Brilliantov and Krapivsky) in
which bubbles grow linearly with time.</p>

<p>Pierre has built a model to explain at which rate Random Apollonian Packings grow after the
insertion of one sphere after the other. The model’s prediction for
the fractal properties of RAP are consistent with numerical
simulations made in two, three and four dimensions.</p>

<p>If you want to explore a RAP in depth, feel free to zoom in that
<a href="https://curl.irmp.ucl.ac.be/~pierre/index.html"><strong>picture</strong></a>, it
contains more than a million spheres.</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Bubble nucleation is a phenomenon ubiquitous in physics, with applications ranging from the geometry of tree crowns, the structure of porous media and of sphere packing. Bubbles also find applications in cosmology such as the characterization of cosmic voids in the large scale structure and the signatures of cosmological phase transitions. In a new preprint, Pierre proposes a new method to determine the fractal properties of the so-called Random Apollonian Packing.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/09/26/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2022-09-26T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-26T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/09/26/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/09/26/seminar.html"><![CDATA[<p>The next cosmology seminar takes place on <strong>Friday 30th</strong> of
September, seminar <strong>room E349</strong> at <strong>2pm</strong>. Our guest speaker will be
<strong>Nilanjandev Bhaumik</strong> from the Indian Institute of Science (Bangalore, India).</p>

<hr />

<p>At 2pm, room E349, Nilanjan Bhaumik (IIS), will be talking about</p>

<h3 id="stochastic-gravitational-waves-background-to-probe-the-reheating-histories-in-the-presence-of-primordial-black-holes">Stochastic gravitational waves background to probe the reheating histories in the presence of primordial black holes</h3>

<p><em>Primordial black hole (PBH) is one of the most promising cold dark
 matter candidates in recent years. The signature of PBHs in the
 stochastic gravitational-wave background (SGWB) is natural as PBH
 formation requires a significant amplification in inflationary scalar
 curvature perturbation, which sources the tensor perturbation in
 second order and amplifies the SGWB. We explore this possibility to
 probe different possible reheating histories. We find that any change
 in reheating histories can shift the PBH mass range and the peak
 frequency of SGWB. Still, only the matter-dominated reheating phase
 can lead to an additional resonant amplification in SGWB at a very
 high frequency.
 Isocurvature perturbation from PBH distributions
 contributes to the adiabatic perturbation. It also leads to
 detectable amplification in the induced GW background and can
 contribute to Baryogenesis for ultra-low mass PBHs, which can
 dominate the universe for a small duration. Combining these two
 effects can help us probe primordial black hole scenarios and details
 of reheating histories, leaving diverse implications for cosmology
 and particle physics.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The next cosmology seminar takes place on Friday 30th of September, seminar room E349 at 2pm. Our guest speaker will be Nilanjandev Bhaumik from the Indian Institute of Science (Bangalore, India).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Slow-roll Inflation at N3LO</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/09/15/2205.12608.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Slow-roll Inflation at N3LO" /><published>2022-09-15T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-15T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/09/15/2205.12608</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/09/15/2205.12608.html"><![CDATA[<p>Cosmic Inflation, the most favoured scenario of the early Universe,
implies that all forms of matter and radiation observed today are the
outcome of quantum fluctuations occurring around the event horizon of a
exponentially fast accelerating space-time. Clearing the ground for
the incoming spatial and ground based cosmological observations,
<a href="/members/auclair.html"><strong>Pierre</strong></a> and
<a href="/members/chris.html"><strong>Christophe</strong></a> have derived, at an
unprecedented level of precision, the shape of the expected power
spectra of both the quantum-generated gravitational waves and
curvature perturbations.</p>

<p>Cosmic Inflation is an hypothetical early phase of accelerated
expansion that has occurred before the first billionth of a second of
existence of our Universe. It provides a natural mechanism to explain
the observed flatness of our Universe today and naturally solves the
so-called horizon problems of the Big-Bang model.</p>

<p>In a spectacular way, the quantum fluctuations that are inherently
sourced during the inflationary era are exactly what is needed to
explain the origin of the cosmological perturbations: the <strong>seeds of the
galaxies</strong> of today.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2205.12608/ngc83.jpg" alt="ngc83" title="Galaxy Group NGC80" /></p>

<p>These quantum fluctuations are deeply rooted in gravity and appear as
both primordial gravitational waves \(h_{ij}\) and curvature
perturbations \(\zeta\), with very peculiar correlation functions. In
Ref. <a class="citation" href="#auclair:2022yxs">[1]</a>, we have pushed to third order the
calculation of these correlation functions. They are completely
determined by the Hubble parameter during inflation \(H(N)\) and its
logarithmic derivatives, \(\epsilon_i(N) \equiv \mathrm{d}\ln H /
\mathrm{d} \ln N\) (the so-called Hubble flow functions). Here \(N=\ln a\)
is the logarithm of the scale factor \(a\).</p>

<p>Slow-roll inflation <strong>predicts</strong> the correlation functions to be
given by these spectra:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2205.12608/pzeta.png" alt="pzeta" title="Scalar Power Spectrum" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2205.12608/ph.png" alt="ph" title="Tensor Power Spectrum" /></p>

<p>They are expanded around an observable wavenumber
\(k_*=0.05\,\mathrm{Mpc}^{-1}\) and readily testable with the
incoming cosmological observations from the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euclid_(spacecraft)"><strong>Euclid</strong></a> and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LiteBIRD"><strong>LiteBird</strong></a> space
telescopes, but also from the ground based
<a href="https://cmb-s4.org/"><strong>CMB-S4</strong></a> telescopes and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simons_Observatory"><strong>Simons
Observatory</strong></a>. Are
we going to detect a non-vanishing \(\epsilon_{3*}\)?</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cosmic Inflation, the most favoured scenario of the early Universe, implies that all forms of matter and radiation observed today are the outcome of quantum fluctuations occurring around the event horizon of a exponentially fast accelerating space-time. Clearing the ground for the incoming spatial and ground based cosmological observations, Pierre and Christophe have derived, at an unprecedented level of precision, the shape of the expected power spectra of both the quantum-generated gravitational waves and curvature perturbations.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">BEL Center exhibition</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2022/06/22/BEL.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BEL Center exhibition" /><published>2022-06-22T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-06-22T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2022/06/22/BEL</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2022/06/22/BEL.html"><![CDATA[<p>Anticipating the opening of the Brout-Englert-Lemaître Center, a few
aesthetic pictures associated with our researches will be on display
during the “Walk in the Park” event, on Saturday the 25th at the
Tournay Solvay Park (11am).</p>

<h3 id="anamorphosis-from-the-big-bang">Anamorphosis from the Big-Bang</h3>

<p>On display, you’ll find a black and white fractal image, extracted
from Ref. <a class="citation" href="#clesse:2009ur">[1]</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/outreach/anamorphosis.png" alt="ichybrid" /></p>

<p><em>Cosmic inflation is an hypothetic phase of accelerated expansion of
the Universe, a tiny fraction of second after the Big-Bang, induced by
the existence of a scalar field in the early Universe and suspected to
be at the origin of the present structures of the Universe. During
inflation, in about \(10^{-35}\) second, the distance between any two
points in the Universe separated by one meter becomes larger than the
distance to the farthest galaxies. This makes inflation one of the
most fascinating phenomena in Science.</em></p>

<p><em>This picture shows the results of more than 4 millions numerical
simulations of inflation in a model with two scalar fields, called
hybrid inflation, for which inflation stops due a broken symmetry,
similar to the Brout-Englert-Higgs mechanism. The \(x\) and \(y\) axis
represent the initial value of each scalar field, a white dot indicate
that the simulation led to enough expansion for being compatible with
our Universe, whereas for black dots, there is no, or not enough,
inflation.</em></p>

<p><em>Before these results were obtained in Ref. <a class="citation" href="#clesse:2009ur">[1]</a>,
at ULB and UCLouvain, it was thought that only the thin vertical white
band could lead to inflation, suggesting a fine-tuning problem. This
picture shows that, on the contrary, a large number of initial
conditions are satisfactory and form a complex fractal structure. In
analogy with anamorphosis, a phenomena consisting in the distortion of
an image through an optical instrument, one can see this fractal
structure as the image of the thin vertical band seen through the
potential associated with the scalar fields, playing the role of the
optical instrument.</em></p>

<hr />

<h3 id="the-night-sky-by-gaia">The night sky by GAIA</h3>

<p>Using the recently released public domain data DR3 from the GAIA satellite
(ESA), we have reconstructed a view of our night sky, as you would see
it with very sensitive eyes, eyes that would allow you to actually see
daylight colors but in the dark.</p>

<p><a href="https://curl.irmp.ucl.ac.be/vlimages/gaialaxy.html"><img src="/assets/images/outreach/gaialaxy.png" alt="gaialaxy" /></a></p>

<p><em>This image represents the integrated light flux coming from all faint
sources of light, of magnitude greater than \(10\), in human-visible
colors (sRGB). These sources are mostly stars from our own Galaxy and
have been measured by the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaia_(spacecraft)"><strong>Gaia
satellite</strong></a>
(ESA/Gaia/DPAC). There are more than 1.5 billion of stars accounted
for in this image. The image making code is available here:
<a href="https://github.com/eatdust/gaialaxy"><strong>gaialaxy</strong></a>.</em></p>

<hr />

<h3 id="the-cosmic-strings-microwave-sky">The Cosmic Strings Microwave Sky</h3>

<p>Extracted from Ref. <a class="citation" href="#ringeval:2012tk">[2]</a>, a small piece of a
computer generated all sky map of the Cosmic Microwave Background
generated by Cosmic Strings.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/outreach/gradmap.png" alt="gradmag" /></p>

<p><em>These objects are line-like defects in the fabric of space-time and
could have been formed in the earliest times of the Universe history.
This picture is a small part of a full sky image computed using
\(12000\) processors of one of the largest world computer at that
time: the Cray XE6
<a href="https://www.nersc.gov/about/nersc-history/history-of-systems/"><strong>Hopper</strong></a>
at the <a href="https://www.nersc.gov/"><strong>NERSC</strong></a>. This image has been used
to search for Cosmic Strings in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planck_(spacecraft)"><strong>Planck
satellite</strong></a> data
(ESA).</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Anticipating the opening of the Brout-Englert-Lemaître Center, a few aesthetic pictures associated with our researches will be on display during the “Walk in the Park” event, on Saturday the 25th at the Tournay Solvay Park (11am).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stochastic gravitational waves from long cosmic strings</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/05/30/2205.04349.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stochastic gravitational waves from long cosmic strings" /><published>2022-05-30T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-05-30T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/05/30/2205.04349</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/05/30/2205.04349.html"><![CDATA[<p>A cosmic strings network present in our Universe should be incessantly
emitting gravitational waves. An absolute lower limit of the expected
signal can be found by determining the gravitational waves created
by the back bones of the network: the long cosmic
strings. <a href="/members/dacunha.html"><strong>Disrael</strong></a> and <a href="/members/chris.html"><strong>Christophe</strong></a>, in collaboration with
<a href="http://www2.iap.fr/users/bouchet/bouchet.html"><strong>François R. Bouchet</strong></a>, have
computed this irreducible contribution using new numerical
simulations of Nambu-Goto cosmic strings.</p>

<p>In Ref. <a class="citation" href="#dacunha:2022chf">[1]</a>, we have run new simulations of
Nambu-Goto cosmic strings evolving during the radiation, the
transition, and the matter eras to compute the unequal time
correlators of the anisotropic stress tensor associated with the long
strings. The following figure shows a snapshot of one of these
simulation, the long strings have been represented in white whereas
all the other objects are loops, see Ref. <a class="citation" href="#ringeval:2017eww">[2]</a>
and <a href="/news/2019/04/07/1903.06685.html">this post</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2205.04349/snapshot_h063.png" alt="nbsimu" /></p>

<p>This correlator sources the gravitational waves and it allows us to
solve for their creation, and propagation, all along the Universe
history. By using the Green’s function method we can then predict the
strain, \(k^2 \mathcal{P}_h\), and the energy density parameter
\(\Omega_{\mathrm{GW}}^{\mathrm{mat}}\) of the gravitational waves
that can be measured today. Their power spectra are represented below
as a function of the wavenumber \(k\).</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2205.04349/k2calPh.png" alt="k2calPh" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2205.04349/OmegaGW.png" alt="OmegaGW" /></p>

<p>In these figures, the exact numerical result is represented in black
while the blue and red curves show some semi-analytical approximations
that we had proposed in a previous paper, calibrated using the
amplitude found with the simulations, see Ref. <a class="citation" href="#dacunha:2021wyy">[3]</a>. The only significant deviations show up around \(k/\mathcal{H}_0
\simeq 100\), which corresponds to the transition between the
radiation and matter era. An interesting point to notice is that most
of strain signal is actually generated by the long cosmic strings in
the matter era, i.e., close to us.</p>

<p>As we discuss in Ref. <a class="citation" href="#dacunha:2022chf">[1]</a>, this signal is quite
small, but reachable by the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laser_Interferometer_Space_Antenna"><strong>LISA</strong></a>
satellites. These ones will be sensitive to long strings that are
undetectable today in the Cosmic Microwave Background.</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A cosmic strings network present in our Universe should be incessantly emitting gravitational waves. An absolute lower limit of the expected signal can be found by determining the gravitational waves created by the back bones of the network: the long cosmic strings. Disrael and Christophe, in collaboration with François R. Bouchet, have computed this irreducible contribution using new numerical simulations of Nambu-Goto cosmic strings.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gravitational waves from freely decaying turbulence</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/05/12/2205.02588.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gravitational waves from freely decaying turbulence" /><published>2022-05-12T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-05-12T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/05/12/2205.02588</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/05/12/2205.02588.html"><![CDATA[<p>As our Universe has expanded and cooled, it is suspected that it has
undergone different phase transitions. In particular, first order
cosmological phase transitions provide a compelling source of
Gravitational Waves (GWs) and this is particularly interesting in the
context of the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laser_Interferometer_Space_Antenna"><strong>LISA</strong></a>. In
a recent publication, <a href="/members/auclair.html"><strong>Pierre</strong></a> and his
collaborators proposed a new accurate semi-analytical model for
predicting the GW signal generated by a turbulent phase in the
aftermath of a first order phase transition.</p>

<p>LISA can potentially detect GW signals from first order phase transitions occurring
in the energy range \(100\,\mathrm{GeV}\) – \(1 \,
\mathrm{TeV}\). There are several processes possibly leading to
sizeable emission of GWs:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Bubble percolation, with the consequent breaking of spherical symmetry, is the most direct one</li>
  <li>Bubble collision</li>
  <li>Sound waves produced in the fluid by expanding bubbles</li>
  <li>Decaying turbulence in the fluid</li>
</ul>

<p>In Ref. <a class="citation" href="#auclair:2022jod">[1]</a>, we propose a new model to the decay and
decorrelation of a purely vortical velocity field and calculate the
subsequent GW signal. To confirm the accuracy and relevance of the
model, we have carried out a campaign of massively parallel direct
numerical simulations of decaying turbulence. The figure below shows
a slice across one of these simulations.</p>

<p>The following figure shows the initial conditions for the velocity
field in real space
<img src="/assets/images/2205.02588/V_0000.png" alt="V0" /></p>

<p>After some evolution, the velocity field decays and small scale
structures develop. The next figure shows the velocity field
after \(20\)
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddy_(fluid_dynamics)"><strong>eddy</strong></a>
turnover times
<img src="/assets/images/2205.02588/V_0001.png" alt="V1" /></p>

<p>Based on this modelling, we provide an approximate analytical form for
the GW signal which could be readily used within the LISA
collaboration to search for it. In the figure below, coloured lines
show the results of the simulations, the black line the
semi-analytical model and the grey line the analytical form usable for
LISA.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2205.02588/money_plot.png" alt="money" /></p>

<p>Other new findings are presented in Ref. <a class="citation" href="#auclair:2022jod">[1]</a>. For instance, including an initial growth phase for the turbulent
flow is shown to heavily influences the spectral shape of the
SGWB. This highlights the importance of a complete understanding of
the turbulence generation mechanism.</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As our Universe has expanded and cooled, it is suspected that it has undergone different phase transitions. In particular, first order cosmological phase transitions provide a compelling source of Gravitational Waves (GWs) and this is particularly interesting in the context of the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna LISA. In a recent publication, Pierre and his collaborators proposed a new accurate semi-analytical model for predicting the GW signal generated by a turbulent phase in the aftermath of a first order phase transition.]]></summary></entry></feed>