<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://curl.group/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://curl.group/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-09-21T10:49:23+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/</id><title type="html">CURL</title><subtitle>Research Group</subtitle><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><entry><title type="html">La Cosmologie Moderne</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/09/21/CAAPC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="La Cosmologie Moderne" /><published>2018-09-21T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-21T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/09/21/CAAPC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/09/21/CAAPC.html">&lt;p&gt;For the equinox, S. Clesse gives a public lecture on The Big-Bang
model for the Cercle des Astronomes Amateurs de Charleroi. More
information there:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://caapc.be/calendrier%202011.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CAAPS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/cosmologie_Charleroi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;CAAPC_first_slide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">For the equinox, S. Clesse gives a public lecture on The Big-Bang model for the Cercle des Astronomes Amateurs de Charleroi. More information there:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Belgian Gravitational Waves meeting</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2018/09/12/BGW.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Belgian Gravitational Waves meeting" /><published>2018-09-12T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-12T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2018/09/12/BGW</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2018/09/12/BGW.html">&lt;p&gt;On Thursday 25th, we have the pleasure to host the Belgian
Gravitational Waves meeting. It starts at &lt;strong&gt;2pm&lt;/strong&gt;, seminar &lt;strong&gt;room
E349&lt;/strong&gt;. Our guest speakers are &lt;strong&gt;Stefan Antusch&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Giulia
Cusin&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fys.kuleuven.be/gwc/activities-folder/GWseminars&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GW meetings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 14:00, Stefan Antusch (Basel U.), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;oscillons-and-gravitational-waves-from-preheating-after-inflation&quot;&gt;Oscillons and gravitational waves from preheating after inflation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We discuss the preheating phase after inflation in particle physics
motivated models of the early universe. We show that the non-linear
dynamics after hilltop-type inflation models, where inflation can be
linked to a particle physics phase transition, can lead to the
formation of oscillons, comparatively long-lived and strong local
fluctuations of the inflaton field. Similar types of scalar field
potentials also appear in the KKLT scenario in string phenomenology,
and oscillons can form for the modulus field. We argue that when the
oscillons are asymmetric for a sufficiently long period, they can
generate a peak in the otherwise rather broad gravitational wave
spectrum produced during the earlier phases of preheating.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a coffee break, at 15:30, Giulia Cusin (Oxford U.) will talk about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;astrophysical-background-of-gravitational-waves-from-cosmology-to-a-new-era-of-precision-astrophysics&quot;&gt;Astrophysical background of gravitational waves: from cosmology to a new era of precision astrophysics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The astrophysical background of gravitational waves (AGWB) is made up
by the incoherent superposition of gravitational wave signals emitted
by a large number of resolved and unresolved astrophysical sources
from the onset of stellar activity until today, and that we collect at
our detectors. I present a theoretical framework to fully characterize
the AGWB in terms of energy density anisotropies and polarization and
I show the first numerical predictions for the angular power spectra
of anisotropies in different frequency bands and for
cross-correlations with electromagnetic observables such as weak
leaning and galaxy number counts. l then illustrate and discuss the
astrophysical implications of this study.  By properly modelling the
properties of the AGWB, it will be possible to extract for the first
time precise data on galactic and stellar physics and on astrophysical
processes of GW emission. In the same way as the discovery and study
of the cosmic microwave background has represented a turning point for
cosmology, the study of the AGWB will represent a true revolution for
astrophysics eventually leading to a new era of precision
astrophysics.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">On Thursday 25th, we have the pleasure to host the Belgian Gravitational Waves meeting. It starts at 2pm, seminar room E349. Our guest speakers are Stefan Antusch and Giulia Cusin.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interview for ScienceToday</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/09/05/ScienceToday.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview for ScienceToday" /><published>2018-09-05T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-05T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/09/05/ScienceToday</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/09/05/ScienceToday.html">&lt;p&gt;The publication of the Planck 2018 results is featured in the
ScienceToday UCL website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://uclouvain.be/fr/sciencetoday/actualites/l-heritage-de-planck.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L’héritage de Planck&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">The publication of the Planck 2018 results is featured in the ScienceToday UCL website.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The 2018 Planck results are public!</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2018/07/17/Planck2018.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 2018 Planck results are public!" /><published>2018-07-17T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-07-17T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2018/07/17/Planck2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2018/07/17/Planck2018.html">&lt;p&gt;Celebrating the anniversary of George Lemaître, the final 2018 release
of the Planck satellite measurements have been published today on the
ESA website and the arXiv. They currently provide the strongest
constraints on the Big-Bang model, and much more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All papers are there: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cosmos.esa.int/web/planck/publications#Planck2018&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planck 2018 results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first paper on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1807.06205&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;legacy of
Planck&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; provides a nice overview
of what Planck has been achieving since its launch in 2009!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">Celebrating the anniversary of George Lemaître, the final 2018 release of the Planck satellite measurements have been published today on the ESA website and the arXiv. They currently provide the strongest constraints on the Big-Bang model, and much more!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Two cosmology seminars in a row!</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2018/06/27/seminars.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two cosmology seminars in a row!" /><published>2018-06-27T14:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-27T14:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2018/06/27/seminars</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2018/06/27/seminars.html">&lt;p&gt;This Wednesday, we have not one but two cosmology seminars in a row!
We have the pleasure to receive &lt;strong&gt;Mateo Martinelli&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Alkistis Pourtsidou&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 13:00, Mateo Martinelli (Leiden U., Euclid), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;future-constraints-on-parametrized-modified-gravity-the-impact-of-non-linear-scales-and-of-theoretical-priors&quot;&gt;Future constraints on parametrized modified gravity: the impact of	non linear scales and of theoretical priors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this talk I will present forecasted constraints on
Modified Gravity using Galaxy Clustering and Weak Lensing
measurements. I will explore different possible phenomenological
parametrizations for Modified Gravity models, encoding the effects of
these modifications in two generic functions (η and μ) of time and
space which affect the Poisson equation and the so-called
gravitational slip. I will focus on forecasts for future surveys and I
will highlight the constraining power gained when including non linear
scales in the analysis using phenomenological prescription for the
modelling of these scales in the Modified Gravity framework.  I will
then discuss how it is possible to connect phenomenological
parameterizations to viable theories of modified gravity, imposing
theoretical conditions on the reconstructed functions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a coffee break, at 14:30, Alkistis Pourtsidou (Queen Mary U.,
SKA, Euclid) will talk about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cosmology-with-neutral-hydrogen-hi-intensity-mapping&quot;&gt;Cosmology with neutral hydrogen (HI) intensity mapping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I will introduce the innovative technique of HI intensity
mapping, which allows for precise cosmological measurements in the
radio wavelength. After talking about the current status of intensity
mapping measurements, I will focus on forthcoming surveys using
instruments like MeerKAT/SKA and CHIME to probe dark energy as well as
galaxy evolution. I will also present synergies between optical galaxy
and radio intensity mapping surveys in order to probe dark energy and
gravity, mitigate systematic effects, calibrate photometric redshifts,
and measure primordial non-gaussianity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">This Wednesday, we have not one but two cosmology seminars in a row! We have the pleasure to receive Mateo Martinelli and Alkistis Pourtsidou.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An invitation to grand-parents and their grand-children to discover together the secrets of our Universe</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/06/04/UDA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An invitation to grand-parents and their grand-children to discover together the secrets of our Universe" /><published>2018-06-04T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-04T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/06/04/UDA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/06/04/UDA.html">&lt;p&gt;The 4th of July, Sébastien will be presenting two outreach activities
dedicated to children and their grand-parents, organized by the
&lt;em&gt;Université des Aînés&lt;/em&gt; of UCLouvain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.universitedesaines.be/fiche-formation.php?categorie=435&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L’Univers selon les petits: Alice et le Big-Bang (6-10
ans)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.universitedesaines.be/fiche-formation.php?categorie=444&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L’Univers selon les grands: les plus belles images de l’Univers
(+10
ans)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/smile.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;smile&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">The 4th of July, Sébastien will be presenting two outreach activities dedicated to children and their grand-parents, organized by the Université des Aînés of UCLouvain.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Article in the astronomy magazine “Astrosurf”</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/06/01/ASM92.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Article in the astronomy magazine &quot;Astrosurf&quot;" /><published>2018-06-01T13:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-01T13:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/06/01/ASM92</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/06/01/ASM92.html">&lt;p&gt;Following our exploration of using small non-professional telescopes
for optical follow-up of Planck cluster candidates, see Ref. &lt;a href=&quot;#boucher:2018xvk&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/news/2018/01/01/1801.04124.html&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;, we have published an article entitled
“Mesure du redshift d’amas de galaxies” in the French astronomy
magazine &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.astrosurf.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Astrosurf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/ASM92_Sommaire_1200.png&quot; alt=&quot;astrosurf&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">Following our exploration of using small non-professional telescopes for optical follow-up of Planck cluster candidates, see Ref. [1] and this post, we have published an article entitled “Mesure du redshift d’amas de galaxies” in the French astronomy magazine Astrosurf.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Primordial vs Astrophysical Origin of Black Holes</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2018/05/18/PBHCERN.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Primordial vs Astrophysical Origin of Black Holes" /><published>2018-05-18T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-18T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2018/05/18/PBHCERN</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2018/05/18/PBHCERN.html">&lt;p&gt;From May 14th to 18th, S. Clesse is organizing the first international
conference dedicated to primordial black holes, held at CERN, Geneva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information, slides and recording of the presentations, are
available &lt;a href=&quot;https://indico.cern.ch/event/686745/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">From May 14th to 18th, S. Clesse is organizing the first international conference dedicated to primordial black holes, held at CERN, Geneva.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Des trous noirs nés une milli-seconde après le Big-Bang</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/05/04/maphyl.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Des trous noirs nés une milli-seconde après le Big-Bang" /><published>2018-05-04T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-04T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/05/04/maphyl</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/05/04/maphyl.html">&lt;p&gt;Lecture by S. Clesse, invited by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.maphyl.com&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MaPhyl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; ASBL (association of alumini
students of the UCL in Mathematics and Physics).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;French abstract: &lt;em&gt;La détection d’ondes gravitationnelles issues de la
fusion de trous noirs par l’expérience LIGO/VIRGO, couronnée du Prix
Nobel de Physique 2017, ouvre une nouvelle ère de l’astronomie
moderne.  Déjà, ces détections ont ravivé le débat sur la nature de la
matière noire.  Elles semblent indiquer la présence d’une population
inattendue de trous noirs dont l’abondance est étrangement compatible
avec celle de la matière noire, dont la nature est encore aujourd’hui
un des grands mystères de la cosmologie.  Ainsi, la matière noire
pourraient être constituée de trous noirs primordiaux formés moins
d’une milli-seconde après le Big-Bang.  Aujourd’hui une série d’autres
observations tendent à corroborer cette hypothèse.  Les détecteurs
d’ondes gravitationnelles de nouvelle génération, tels le Einstein
Telescope qui pourrait être construit à la frontière entre la
Belgique, les Pays-Bas et l’Allemagne, auront la capacité de vérifier,
ou invalider cette hypothèse.  Ils testeront aussi notre compréhension
de l’Univers primordial et de la physique fondamentale à des échelles
d’énergie jusqu’à présent inaccessibles.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">Lecture by S. Clesse, invited by the MaPhyl ASBL (association of alumini students of the UCL in Mathematics and Physics).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">La Cosmologie (pour les nuls)</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/05/02/kotastro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="La Cosmologie (pour les nuls)" /><published>2018-05-02T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-02T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/05/02/kotastro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/05/02/kotastro.html">&lt;p&gt;Public lecture by S. Clesse, organized by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kotastro.be&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kot Astro&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the UCLouvain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;French abstract: &lt;em&gt;Que se passe-t-il si l’on tombe dans un trou noir?
Est-il possible de voyager dans le temps? Qu’y avait-il avant le
Big-Bang? Où s’est-il produit, et dans quoi l’Univers s’étend-il
aujourd’hui? L’Univers a-t-il un bord? Existe-t-il d’autres Univers,
d’autres dimensions?  Lorsqu’on discute cosmologie et astrophysique,
ces questions pas si saugrenues reviennent sans cesse. Difficile de
faire la différence entre mythe et réalité, entre scénarios réalistes
et spéculations, entre science et fiction. Nous vous proposons un
voyage un peu fou aux frontières de la Science. Il vous permettra d’y
voir un peu plus clair et de faire le point sur les connaissances et
les défis d’aujourd’hui. Nous lèverons un coin du voile sur notre
Univers, parfois mystérieux, toujours surprenant…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/kot_astro.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;kotastro&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: Typographie conforme à la norme &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ex-abrupto.be/quelle-norme-typographique-suivre/&quot;&gt;NBN Z01-002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">Public lecture by S. Clesse, organized by the Kot Astro of the UCLouvain.</summary></entry></feed>