<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://curl.group/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://curl.group/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-11-18T11:35:20+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/feed.xml</id><title type="html">CURL</title><subtitle>Research Group</subtitle><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><entry><title type="html">Interview for France Culture</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2019/11/18/FranceCulture.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview for France Culture" /><published>2019-11-18T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-18T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2019/11/18/FranceCulture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2019/11/18/FranceCulture.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sébastien Clesse&lt;/strong&gt; is giving an interview for the radio
channel &lt;strong&gt;France Culture&lt;/strong&gt; on &lt;strong&gt;Tuesday 19th&lt;/strong&gt; of November, from &lt;strong&gt;4pm&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;5pm&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned to the broadcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.franceculture.fr/emissions/la-methode-scientifique&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;La Méthode Scientifique&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">Sébastien Clesse is giving an interview for the radio channel France Culture on Tuesday 19th of November, from 4pm to 5pm.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2019/11/07/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2019-11-07T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-07T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2019/11/07/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2019/11/07/seminar.html">&lt;p&gt;Our next cosmology seminar takes place on &lt;strong&gt;Friday 15th&lt;/strong&gt; of November,
seminar &lt;strong&gt;room E349&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;2pm&lt;/strong&gt;. The speaker is &lt;strong&gt;Jibril Ben Achour&lt;/strong&gt;
from the Yukawa Institute (Kyoto, Japan).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 14:00, room E349, Jibril Ben Achour (Yukawa Institute, Kyoto), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;flrw-cosmology-as-a-conformally-invariant-field-theory-in-1d&quot;&gt;FLRW cosmology as a conformally invariant field theory in 1D&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Over the last decades, conformal field theory (CFT) technics have
played an important role in black hole physics, due to the discovery
of unexpected conformal symmetries in the near horizon of black
hole. Using these technics, crucial features of black hole physics,
among which their spectroscopy, quasi-normal modes, as well as their
state counting have been reproduced using CFT technics.  So far, the
possible existence of similar hidden conformal symmetry in
cosmological spacetimes have been much less investigated.  In this
talk, I will show that the simplest cosmological model, consisting in
the homogeneous and isotropic Einstein-Scalar system, enjoys a
surprising hidden conformal symmetry. I will present in detail this
new structure, the associated Noether’s charge as well as the CVH
algebra which encodes this conformal symmetry at the hamiltonian
level.  Then, I will explain how this cosmological system can be
mapped to the well known conformal mechanics developed by de Alfaro,
Fubini and Furlan, and which provides the simplest example of a
classically conformal field theory in 1d. This conformal structure
extends beyond this simple homogeneous and isotropic setting. I will
briefly discuss the inclusion of a cosmological constant,
anisotropies, self-interacting potential for the scalar field, as well
as work in progress on the fully inhomogeneous Einstein-Scalar system.
Finally, I will discuss the consequences of this new conformal
structure at the quantum level. A major outcome is the possibility to
apply the conformal bootstrap program to quantize the theory. Just as
quantum conformal mechanics, I will show that despite the lack of a
conformally invariant group state, it is possible to find an operator
which reproduces the standard form of the CFT two points function in
quantum cosmology. I will discuss the cosmological interpretation of
this operator and the vacuum state which are used to construct this
correlator.  In the end, this provides a first step to bootstrap
quantum cosmology using this new conformal symmetry.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.13390&quot;&gt;arXiv:1909.13390&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">Our next cosmology seminar takes place on Friday 15th of November, seminar room E349 at 2pm. The speaker is Jibril Ben Achour from the Yukawa Institute (Kyoto, Japan).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Belgian Gravitational Waves meeting</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2019/10/16/BGW.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Belgian Gravitational Waves meeting" /><published>2019-10-16T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-10-16T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2019/10/16/BGW</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2019/10/16/BGW.html">&lt;p&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;Thursday 22th&lt;/strong&gt;, we have the pleasure to host the Belgian
Gravitational Waves meeting. It starts at &lt;strong&gt;2pm&lt;/strong&gt;, seminar &lt;strong&gt;room
E349&lt;/strong&gt;. Our guest speaker is &lt;strong&gt;Chris Belczynski&lt;/strong&gt; and our local
speaker is &lt;strong&gt;Sébastien Clesse&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fys.kuleuven.be/gwc/activities-folder/GWseminars&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GW meetings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 14:00, Chris Belczynski (Copernicus Center, Warsaw, Poland), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gravitational-wave-astrophysics-ligovirgo-bh-bhbh-nsns-ns-mergers&quot;&gt;Gravitational-wave Astrophysics: LIGO/Virgo BH-BH/BH-NS/NS-NS mergers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I will discuss the astrophysical importance of the recent LIGO/Virgo
direct detections of gravitational-waves. Despite the fact that massive
BH-BH dominance in gravitational-wave signal was predicted prior the
detections, it is not at all clear which one of the several formation
scenarios produces these massive mergers. This inhibits astrophysical
information inference from LIGO/Virgo observations, as conclusions are
different within each formation scenario. There is quite an opposite
problem with the first detection of NS-NS merger in an old elliptical
host galaxy, as none of the formation channels can easily recover
rather high NS-NS merger rate estimated by LIGO/Virgo. The recent
detection of BH-NS merger seems to indicate the existence of compact
objects in the first mass gap.
Additionally, all of the ten O1/O2 LIGO/Virgo BH-BH merger detections
have low values for their effective spins. I will demonstrate how this
can be naturally explained within framework of classical binary evolution
scenario of the formation of BH-BH mergers. It appears that magnetic
fields (Tayler-Spruit dynamo) play an important role in efficient
transport of angular momentum and spin-down of massive stars that produce
low-spinning black holes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a coffee break, at 15:30, Sébastien Clesse (CURL, UCLouvain)
will talk about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;primordial-black-hole-predictions-for-black-hole-merger-detections-in-ligovirgo&quot;&gt;Primordial black hole predictions for black hole merger detections in LIGO/Virgo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soon after the first gravitational-wave detection, it has been
suggested that the black hole merger progenitors might have a
primordial origin, and eventually explain all or part of the Dark
Matter in the Universe.  Due to the known thermal history of the
Universe, the primordial black hole (PBH) mass function have specific
features that will be probed by the third observing run of LIGO/Virgo.
The predictions for the mass distribution of black hole merger
progenitors and their spins are distinguishable from the ones of
stellar evolution scenarios, and the upcoming detections will be
decisive to confirm or rule out the scenario.  In addition to explain
mergers around 30 solar masses, PBH predict a second peak around 2
solar mass, due to the boost of PBH formation at the QCD transition,
and some mergers above 60 solar masses, in the mass gap, with low mass
ratios, and involving one sub-solar black hole.  These features are
universal, whatever is the underlying PBH formation scenario and their
abundance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">On Thursday 22th, we have the pleasure to host the Belgian Gravitational Waves meeting. It starts at 2pm, seminar room E349. Our guest speaker is Chris Belczynski and our local speaker is Sébastien Clesse.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Post-doctoral opening in Gravitational Wave Cosmology</title><link href="https://curl.group/jobs/2019/10/09/ARC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Post-doctoral opening in Gravitational Wave Cosmology" /><published>2019-10-09T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-10-09T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/jobs/2019/10/09/ARC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/jobs/2019/10/09/ARC.html">&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce the opening of a &lt;strong&gt;post-doctoral position&lt;/strong&gt;
in Gravitational Wave Cosmology at CURL (Cosmology, Universe and
Relativity at Louvain), Louvain University (Belgium), starting fall
2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applicants with expertises in gravitational wave signatures of early
universe physics, stochastic gravitational wave background, cosmic
defects, primordial black holes, cosmic inflation, as well as data
analysis for current and future gravitational wave interferometers,
such as LIGO/Virgo and LISA, are particularly encouraged to apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appointment is available for two years, and could possibly be extended
to 3 years depending on mutual satisfaction and available funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The position is supported by a joint ARC research program in gravitational
wave physics between the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cp3.phys.ucl.ac.be&quot;&gt;CP3 center&lt;/a&gt; and
the &lt;a href=&quot;https://curl.irmp.ucl.ac.be&quot;&gt;CURL group&lt;/a&gt; at UCLouvain and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.star.uliege.be&quot;&gt;STAR
institute&lt;/a&gt; at Université de
Liège. Computing resources and support for travelling are excellent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letters of application (including a curriculum vitae, a list of
publications, a brief statement of research interests) and at least
two recommendation letters from senior scientists should be submitted
on-line, by the 15th of January 2020, at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cp3.irmp.ucl.ac.be/jobs/59&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;https://cp3.irmp.ucl.ac.be/jobs/59&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;christophe.ringeval@uclouvain.be
Cosmology, Universe and Relativity at Louvain
Institute of Mathematics and Physics
Louvain University
2, Chemin du Cyclotron
1348 Louvain-la-Neuve
Belgium
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of our current interests can be consulted on the CURL
website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://curl.group&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;curl.group&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Jobs" /><summary type="html">We are happy to announce the opening of a post-doctoral position in Gravitational Wave Cosmology at CURL (Cosmology, Universe and Relativity at Louvain), Louvain University (Belgium), starting fall 2020.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmic Conundra explained by Primordial Black Holes?</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2019/07/01/1906.08217.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmic Conundra explained by Primordial Black Holes?" /><published>2019-07-01T10:42:07+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-01T10:42:07+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2019/07/01/1906.08217</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2019/07/01/1906.08217.html">&lt;p&gt;The known thermal history of the Universe is expected to shape the
mass function of primordial black
holes. &lt;a href=&quot;/members/clesse.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sébastien&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernard_Carr&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bernard
Carr&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://uam.academia.edu/JuanGarciaBellido&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Juan
García-Bellido&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.su.se/profiles/fflor-1.191847&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Florian Kühnel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; shed a
new light on a series of unexplained cosmic conundra in Ref.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#carr:2019kxo&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/1906.08217/fPBH.png&quot; alt=&quot;fPBH&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This figure shows some expected mass fraction distributions of
primordial black holes as dark matter and the limits imposed by
various astrophysical probes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">The known thermal history of the Universe is expected to shape the mass function of primordial black holes. Sébastien, Bernard Carr, Juan García-Bellido and Florian Kühnel shed a new light on a series of unexplained cosmic conundra in Ref.[1].</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are we born near a black hole?</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2019/06/01/HSEWB.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are we born near a black hole?" /><published>2019-06-01T10:42:07+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-01T10:42:07+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2019/06/01/HSEWB</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2019/06/01/HSEWB.html">&lt;p&gt;Primordial black holes could not only explain the dark matter, but
also the origin of the ordinary matter in the
Universe. &lt;a href=&quot;/members/clesse.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sébastien&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernard_Carr&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bernard
Carr&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://uam.academia.edu/JuanGarciaBellido&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Juan
García-Bellido&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; propose
a new baryogenesis scenario in Refs.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#garcia-bellido:2019vlf&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#carr:2019hud&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When density fluctuations collapse gravitationally in the early
Universe to form primordial black holes, all the conditions are met to
produce the observed baryon asymmetry around the collapsing
regions. Moreover, this scenario naturally explains why the Dark
Matter and Baryons have similar densities. No parameter tuning is
required if these density fluctuations are due to the stochastic
quantum fluctuations of a light spectator field during inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/1904.11482/sketche.png&quot; alt=&quot;baryo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above figure is a qualitative representation of the three steps
in our scenario:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(A) Gravitational collapse to a PBH of the curvature fluctuation at
horizon re-entry.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(B) Sphaleron transition in hot spot around the PBH, producing
baryons locally through electroweak baryogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(C) Propagation of baryons to rest of Universe through jets,
resulting in the observed Baryon Asymmetry of the Universe.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">Primordial black holes could not only explain the dark matter, but also the origin of the ordinary matter in the Universe. Sébastien, Bernard Carr and Juan García-Bellido propose a new baryogenesis scenario in Refs.[2] and [2].</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The shape of cosmic string loop production functions</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2019/04/07/1903.06685.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The shape of cosmic string loop production functions" /><published>2019-04-07T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-07T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2019/04/07/1903.06685</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2019/04/07/1903.06685.html">&lt;p&gt;We have recently made public a rather technical paper in which we
explicitly and unambiguously calculate the cosmic string loop number
density distribution in our universe coming from various motivated
loop production functions. Such a density distribution crucially
determines the spectrum of their emitted gravitational waves, a
smooking gun for their potential discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apc.univ-paris7.fr/APC_CS/fr/auclair-pierre&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pierre Auclair&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kcl.ac.uk/nms/depts/physics/people/academicstaff/sakellariadou&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mairi Sakellariadou&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apc.univ-paris7.fr/APC_CS/fr/users/steer&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Danièle Steer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, we have
carefuly explored in Ref.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#auclair:2019zoz&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; the consequences of
changing the slope of the Polchinski-Rocha loop production function to the actual
observable cosmic string loop distribution. This is the parameter
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\chi&lt;/script&gt; in the next plot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/1903.06685/loopprod.png&quot; alt=&quot;lpf&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the cases we have referred to as “sub-critical”, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\chi &lt; (3 \nu -
1)/2 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;, corresponding to steep slopes in the previous figure, we
recover the results of Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#lorenz:2010sm&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. The parameter
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\nu&lt;/script&gt; encodes the growing rate of the scale factor &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;a(t)&lt;/script&gt;, namely,
we assume &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;a(t) \propto t^\nu&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For shallower slopes, the so-called “critical” and “super-critical”
cases, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\chi \ge (3\nu-1)/2&lt;/script&gt;, we find that either the loop
distribution incessantly grows, or, with some regularisation, reaches a
stationnary distribution whose shape depends on what happens on the
larger length scales. This is best illustrated by the following plot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/1903.06685/diraccomp.png&quot; alt=&quot;diraccomp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It compares the loop number density produced by assuming an infinitely
sharp loop production function peaked at &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma = 0.1&lt;/script&gt; (green
curve) with a (regularised) super-critical Polchinski-Rocha
distribution having &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\chi &gt; 0.25&lt;/script&gt; (purple curve), in the radiation
era (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\nu=1/2&lt;/script&gt;). As this plot shows, the gravitational backreaction
scale, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma_\mathrm{c}&lt;/script&gt;, at which the loop production function is
cut &lt;strong&gt;always matters&lt;/strong&gt; and is responsible for the plateau on the
purple curve at small &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt; values. The existence of a second
plateau around &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma \simeq 10^{-6}&lt;/script&gt; comes from the Infra-Red
sensitivity of all super-critical loop production functions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">We have recently made public a rather technical paper in which we explicitly and unambiguously calculate the cosmic string loop number density distribution in our universe coming from various motivated loop production functions. Such a density distribution crucially determines the spectrum of their emitted gravitational waves, a smooking gun for their potential discovery.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A large mass hierarchy from a small non-minimal coupling</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2019/04/02/1903.03544.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A large mass hierarchy from a small non-minimal coupling" /><published>2019-04-02T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-02T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2019/04/02/1903.03544</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2019/04/02/1903.03544.html">&lt;p&gt;In a recent preprint, we discuss the possibility that both the Planck
mass and the dark energy scale are dynamically generated by stochastic
effects during inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of the energy scales involved in gravitation, the Planck mass
&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M_\mathrm{Pl} \simeq 10^{18}\,\mathrm{GeV}&lt;/script&gt; and the cosmological
constant energy scale &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\rho_{\Lambda}^{1/4} \simeq 10^{-3}\,
\mathrm{eV}&lt;/script&gt; differ by many orders of magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with &lt;a href=&quot;/members/suyama.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teruaki Suyama&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.th.phys.titech.ac.jp/cosmo/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Masahide
Yamaguchi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.th.phys.titech.ac.jp&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TiTech&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Tokyo), we explore in
Ref.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#ringeval:2019bob&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; the possibility that both have been
dynamically generated from a new and unique ultra light scalar field
that would have experienced super-Hubble quantum fluctuations during
primordial inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scenario is currently passing all cosmological and astrophysical
constraints, and could be proven at work with future gravitational
wave measurements of the non-minimal coupling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">In a recent preprint, we discuss the possibility that both the Planck mass and the dark energy scale are dynamically generated by stochastic effects during inflation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Informal meeting on Primordial Black Holes</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2019/04/01/MiniPBH.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Informal meeting on Primordial Black Holes" /><published>2019-04-01T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-01T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2019/04/01/MiniPBH</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2019/04/01/MiniPBH.html">&lt;p&gt;We hold an informal meeting, organized one day before the Solvay
Workshop on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.solvayinstitutes.be/event/workshop/dark_2019/dark_2019.html&quot;&gt;“The dark side of Black
Holes”&lt;/a&gt;
in Brussels (but not officially related to it), with a few experts on
PBH to discuss recent developments in the field. This takes place
Tuesday 2nd of April, seminar room E349 from 10 am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Registration &lt;a href=&quot;https://agenda.irmp.ucl.ac.be/event/3341/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program starts at 10:00 with Ilia Musco (ICC U. Barcelona)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;threshold-and-abundance-of-primordial-black-holes-dependence-on-the-profile-of-the-cosmological-perturbations&quot;&gt;Threshold and abundance of primordial black holes: dependence on the profile of the cosmological perturbations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Primordial black holes can form in the early Universe from the
 collapse of cosmological perturbations after the cosmological horizon
 crossing. They are possible candidates for the dark matter as well as
 for the seeds of supermassive black holes observed today in the
 centre of galaxies. In calculations of spherically symmetric
 collapse, using a large curvature perturbation in the super horizon
 regime, the initial conditions are specified using the gradient
 expansion approximation in the long wave length limit. The non linear
 evolution is then simulated using a Lagrangian relativistic
 hydrodynamical code. If the perturbation is larger than a threshold
 depending on the equation of state and on the specific shape of the
 perturbation, a black hole is formed. In this talk I will discuss the
 dependence of PBH formation from the initial shape of the curvature
 profile showing the relation between the threshold amplitude and the
 steepness of the perturbation which is linked to the amplitude of the
 pressure gradients that are developing during the collapse. I will
 show how to derive the initial curvature profile form the shape of
 the inflationary power spectrum, which affects also the abundance of
 PBHs. Depending on the model, a proper calculation, using the shape
 of the power spectrum, shows that the abundance of PBHs is
 significantly increased by several order of magnitudes compared to
 previous estimations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:50, Teruaki Suyama (TiTech, Tokyo) will speak about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hidden-universality-in-the-merger-rate-distribution-in-the-primordial-black-hole-scenario&quot;&gt;Hidden universality in the merger rate distribution in the primordial black hole scenario&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It has been proposed that primordial black holes (PBHs) form binaries
 in the radiation dominated era. Once formed, some fraction of them
 may merge within the age of the Universe by gravitational radiation
 reaction. We investigate the merger rate of the PBH binaries when the
 PBH mass function is not monochromatic, which is a generalization of
 the previous studies where the PBHs are assumed to have the same
 mass. After deriving a formula for the merger time probability
 distribution in the PBH mass plane, we evaluate it under two
 different approximations. We identify a quantity constructed from the
 mass-distribution of the merger rate density whose value is close to
 unity for all binary masses independently of the PBH mass
 function. This result suggests that the measurement of this quantity
 is useful for testing the PBH scenario.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lunch, we will have Florian Kuhnel (Oscar Klein Centre,
Stockholm U.) with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;primordial-black-holes---formation-constraints-uncertainties&quot;&gt;Primordial Black Holes - Formation, Constraints, Uncertainties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Primordial black holes are black holes that may have formed in the
 early Universe. Their masses potentially span a range from as low as
 the Planck mass up to many orders of magnitude above the solar
 mass. This, in particular, includes black holes of the order of 10
 solar masses, like those recently discovered by LIGO. These may be of
 primordial origin. In order to quantitatively asses this and related
 scenarios, a profound understanding of the holes’ formation mechanism
 necessary. After a general introduction on primordial black holes, I
 will discuss the most consequential aspects of their formation, and
 elaborate on the observable imprints these may leave. I will give an
 overview about recent abundance limits, discuss the uncertainty of
 these constraints.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, Michael Hawkins (Edimburg O.) will close the day talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-signature-of-primordial-black-holes-in-galaxy-dark-matter-haloes&quot;&gt;The signature of primordial black holes in galaxy dark matter haloes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are several well-known gravitationally lensed quasar systems
 where the quasar images appear to lie well clear of the stars in the
 lensing galaxy. I shall show that in some such cases the stellar
 population cannot account for the observed microlensing. In these
 cases the most plausible bodies responsible for thr lensing are
 primordial black holes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">We hold an informal meeting, organized one day before the Solvay Workshop on “The dark side of Black Holes” in Brussels (but not officially related to it), with a few experts on PBH to discuss recent developments in the field. This takes place Tuesday 2nd of April, seminar room E349 from 10 am.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Inflation after Planck: Judgment Day</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2019/03/01/1902.03951.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inflation after Planck: Judgment Day" /><published>2019-03-01T09:42:07+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-01T09:42:07+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2019/03/01/1902.03951</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2019/03/01/1902.03951.html">&lt;p&gt;The final release of the Planck data 2018, see &lt;a href=&quot;/news/2018/07/17/Planck2018.html&quot;&gt;this
post&lt;/a&gt;, invited
us to finalize a long project in which we discuss the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; status of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inflation_(cosmology)&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cosmic Inflation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with
respect to what we have learned about the early universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a quite long preprint &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#chowdhury:2019otk&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, we are trying to
exhaustively address all the criticisms raised against the inflationary
paradigm and confront them to what the Planck data told
us. The conclusion is short and summarized in the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Although we find that important questions still remain open, we
conclude that the inflationary paradigm is not in trouble but, on the
contrary, has rather been strengthened by the Planck data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re skeptic? Read the paper…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">The final release of the Planck data 2018, see this post, invited us to finalize a long project in which we discuss the actual status of Cosmic Inflation with respect to what we have learned about the early universe.</summary></entry></feed>