<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://curl.group/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://curl.group/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-06-22T20:26:01+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/feed.xml</id><title type="html">CURL</title><subtitle>Research Group</subtitle><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><entry><title type="html">BEL Center exhibition</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2022/06/22/BEL.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BEL Center exhibition" /><published>2022-06-22T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-06-22T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2022/06/22/BEL</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2022/06/22/BEL.html">&lt;p&gt;Anticipating the opening of the Brout-Englert-Lemaître Center, a few
aesthetic pictures associated with our researches will be on display
during the “Walk in the Park” event, on Saturday the 25th at the
Tournay Solvay Park (11am).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;anamorphosis-from-the-big-bang&quot;&gt;Anamorphosis from the Big-Bang&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On display, you’ll find a black and white fractal image, extracted
from Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#clesse:2009ur&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/anamorphosis.png&quot; alt=&quot;ichybrid&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cosmic inflation is an hypothetic phase of accelerated expansion of
the Universe, a tiny fraction of second after the Big-Bang, induced by
the existence of a scalar field in the early Universe and suspected to
be at the origin of the present structures of the Universe. During
inflation, in about \(10^{-35}\) second, the distance between any two
points in the Universe separated by one meter becomes larger than the
distance to the farthest galaxies. This makes inflation one of the
most fascinating phenomena in Science.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This picture shows the results of more than 4 millions numerical
simulations of inflation in a model with two scalar fields, called
hybrid inflation, for which inflation stops due a broken symmetry,
similar to the Brout-Englert-Higgs mechanism. The \(x\) and \(y\) axis
represent the initial value of each scalar field, a white dot indicate
that the simulation led to enough expansion for being compatible with
our Universe, whereas for black dots, there is no, or not enough,
inflation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Before these results were obtained in Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#clesse:2009ur&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;,
at ULB and UCLouvain, it was thought that only the thin vertical white
band could lead to inflation, suggesting a fine-tuning problem. This
picture shows that, on the contrary, a large number of initial
conditions are satisfactory and form a complex fractal structure. In
analogy with anamorphosis, a phenomena consisting in the distortion of
an image through an optical instrument, one can see this fractal
structure as the image of the thin vertical band seen through the
potential associated with the scalar fields, playing the role of the
optical instrument.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-night-sky-by-gaia&quot;&gt;The night sky by GAIA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the recently released public domain data DR3 from the GAIA satellite
(ESA), we have reconstructed a view of our night sky, as you would see
it with very sensitive eyes, eyes that would allow you to actually see
daylight colors but in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/gaialaxy.png&quot; alt=&quot;gaialaxy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This image represents the integrated light flux coming from all faint
sources of light, of magnitude greater than \(10\), in human-visible
colors (sRGB). These sources are mostly stars from our own Galaxy and
have been measured by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaia_(spacecraft)&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gaia
satellite&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(ESA/Gaia/DPAC). There are more than 1.5 billion of stars accounted
for in this image. The image making code is available here:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/eatdust/gaialaxy&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;gaialaxy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-cosmic-strings-microwave-sky&quot;&gt;The Cosmic Strings Microwave Sky&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extracted from Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#ringeval:2012tk&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, a small piece of a
computer generated all sky map of the Cosmic Microwave Background
generated by Cosmic Strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/gradmap.png&quot; alt=&quot;gradmag&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These objects are line-like defects in the fabric of space-time and
could have been formed in the earliest times of the Universe history.
This picture is a small part of a full sky image computed using
\(12000\) processors of one of the largest world computer at that
time: the Cray XE6
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nersc.gov/about/nersc-history/history-of-systems/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hopper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nersc.gov/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NERSC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This image has been used
to search for Cosmic Strings in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planck_(spacecraft)&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planck
satellite&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; data
(ESA).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">Anticipating the opening of the Brout-Englert-Lemaître Center, a few aesthetic pictures associated with our researches will be on display during the “Walk in the Park” event, on Saturday the 25th at the Tournay Solvay Park (11am).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stochastic gravitational waves from long cosmic strings</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/05/30/2205.04349.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stochastic gravitational waves from long cosmic strings" /><published>2022-05-30T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-05-30T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/05/30/2205.04349</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/05/30/2205.04349.html">&lt;p&gt;A cosmic strings network present in our Universe should be incessantly
emitting gravitational waves. An absolute lower limit of the expected
signal can be found by determining the gravitational waves created
by the back bones of the network: the long cosmic
strings. &lt;a href=&quot;/members/dacunha.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disrael&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/members/chris.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christophe&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in collaboration with
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.iap.fr/users/bouchet/bouchet.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;François R. Bouchet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, have
computed this irreducible contribution using new numerical
simulations of Nambu-Goto cosmic strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#dacunha:2022chf&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, we have run new simulations of
Nambu-Goto cosmic strings evolving during the radiation, the
transition, and the matter eras to compute the unequal time
correlators of the anisotropic stress tensor associated with the long
strings. The following figure shows a snapshot of one of these
simulation, the long strings have been represented in white whereas
all the other objects are loops, see Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#ringeval:2017eww&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;/news/2019/04/07/1903.06685.html&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2205.04349/snapshot_h063.png&quot; alt=&quot;nbsimu&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This correlator sources the gravitational waves and it allows us to
solve for their creation, and propagation, all along the Universe
history. By using the Green’s function method we can then predict the
strain, \(k^2 \mathcal{P}_h\), and the energy density parameter
\(\Omega_{\mathrm{GW}}^{\mathrm{mat}}\) of the gravitational waves
that can be measured today. Their power spectra are represented below
as a function of the wavenumber \(k\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2205.04349/k2calPh.png&quot; alt=&quot;k2calPh&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2205.04349/OmegaGW.png&quot; alt=&quot;OmegaGW&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these figures, the exact numerical result is represented in black
while the blue and red curves show some semi-analytical approximations
that we had proposed in a previous paper, calibrated using the
amplitude found with the simulations, see Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#dacunha:2021wyy&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. The only significant deviations show up around \(k/\mathcal{H}_0
\simeq 100\), which corresponds to the transition between the
radiation and matter era. An interesting point to notice is that most
of strain signal is actually generated by the long cosmic strings in
the matter era, i.e., close to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we discuss in Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#dacunha:2022chf&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, this signal is quite
small, but reachable by the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laser_Interferometer_Space_Antenna&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LISA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
satellites. These ones will be sensitive to long strings that are
undetectable today in the Cosmic Microwave Background.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">A cosmic strings network present in our Universe should be incessantly emitting gravitational waves. An absolute lower limit of the expected signal can be found by determining the gravitational waves created by the back bones of the network: the long cosmic strings. Disrael and Christophe, in collaboration with François R. Bouchet, have computed this irreducible contribution using new numerical simulations of Nambu-Goto cosmic strings.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gravitational waves from freely decaying turbulence</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/05/12/2205.02588.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gravitational waves from freely decaying turbulence" /><published>2022-05-12T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-05-12T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/05/12/2205.02588</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/05/12/2205.02588.html">&lt;p&gt;As our Universe has expanded and cooled, it is suspected that it has
undergone different phase transitions. In particular, first order
cosmological phase transitions provide a compelling source of
Gravitational Waves (GWs) and this is particularly interesting in the
context of the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laser_Interferometer_Space_Antenna&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LISA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In
a recent publication, &lt;a href=&quot;/members/auclair.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pierre&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and his
collaborators proposed a new accurate semi-analytical model for
predicting the GW signal generated by a turbulent phase in the
aftermath of a first order phase transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LISA can potentially detect GW signals from first order phase transitions occurring
in the energy range \(100\,\mathrm{GeV}\) – \(1 \,
\mathrm{TeV}\). There are several processes possibly leading to
sizeable emission of GWs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bubble percolation, with the consequent breaking of spherical symmetry, is the most direct one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bubble collision&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sound waves produced in the fluid by expanding bubbles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decaying turbulence in the fluid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#auclair:2022jod&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, we propose a new model to the decay and
decorrelation of a purely vortical velocity field and calculate the
subsequent GW signal. To confirm the accuracy and relevance of the
model, we have carried out a campaign of massively parallel direct
numerical simulations of decaying turbulence. The figure below shows
a slice across one of these simulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following figure shows the initial conditions for the velocity
field in real space
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2205.02588/V_0000.png&quot; alt=&quot;V0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some evolution, the velocity field decays and small scale
structures develop. The next figure shows the velocity field
after \(20\)
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddy_(fluid_dynamics)&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;eddy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
turnover times
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2205.02588/V_0001.png&quot; alt=&quot;V1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this modelling, we provide an approximate analytical form for
the GW signal which could be readily used within the LISA
collaboration to search for it. In the figure below, coloured lines
show the results of the simulations, the black line the
semi-analytical model and the grey line the analytical form usable for
LISA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2205.02588/money_plot.png&quot; alt=&quot;money&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other new findings are presented in Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#auclair:2022jod&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. For instance, including an initial growth phase for the turbulent
flow is shown to heavily influences the spectral shape of the
SGWB. This highlights the importance of a complete understanding of
the turbulence generation mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">As our Universe has expanded and cooled, it is suspected that it has undergone different phase transitions. In particular, first order cosmological phase transitions provide a compelling source of Gravitational Waves (GWs) and this is particularly interesting in the context of the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna LISA. In a recent publication, Pierre and his collaborators proposed a new accurate semi-analytical model for predicting the GW signal generated by a turbulent phase in the aftermath of a first order phase transition.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/05/10/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2022-05-10T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-05-10T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/05/10/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/05/10/seminar.html">&lt;p&gt;The next cosmology seminar takes place on &lt;strong&gt;Thursday 19th&lt;/strong&gt; of
May, seminar &lt;strong&gt;room E349&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;11am&lt;/strong&gt;. Our guest speaker will be
&lt;strong&gt;Hugo Roussille&lt;/strong&gt; from APC (Paris, France).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 11:00, room E349, Hugo Rousille (APC), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;linear-perturbations-of-black-holes-in-dhost-gravity&quot;&gt;Linear perturbations of black holes in DHOST gravity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;General relativity can be tested at many scales using various
 physical systems. A particularly interesting probe is the study of
 the ringdown phase of a binary black hole merger, during which the
 gravitational waves emitted by the newly-formed black hole are well
 described by perturbation theory over a single black hole
 background. The features of these waves depend heavily on the theory
 of gravity underlying the solution and the solution
 itself. Therefore, they can be used both to test GR and rule out some
 black hole solutions. We focus in this talk on the study of new
 behaviours for these waves in scalar-tensor theories in the
 Degenerate Higher-Order Scalar-Tensor (DHOST) class. In such
 theories, the usual dichotomy between axial (odd parity) and polar
 (even parity) perturbations no longer enables one to decouple all
 degrees of freedom since the even parity sector contains one
 additional scalar degree of freedom. Axial perturbations can still be
 completely decoupled: we show that they propagate in an effective
 metric that differs from the background metric, and is not always a
 black hole metric. In the case of polar perturbations, we present a
 systematic approach that extracts the asymptotic behaviour of
 perturbations at spatial infinity and near the horizon directly from
 the perturbed Einstein’s equations. This asymptotic behavior gives
 physical insight about the modes, such as their direction and speed
 of propagation, and allows us to rule out some solutions that
 explicit bad behavior. Furthermore, we can use the obtained
 asymptotic behavior to numerically solve the propagation equations
 and compute quasinormal modes in systems where this was not possible
 before.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">The next cosmology seminar takes place on Thursday 19th of May, seminar room E349 at 11am. Our guest speaker will be Hugo Roussille from APC (Paris, France).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/04/04/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2022-04-04T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-04T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/04/04/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/04/04/seminar.html">&lt;p&gt;The next cosmology seminar takes place on &lt;strong&gt;Thursday 7th&lt;/strong&gt; of
April, seminar &lt;strong&gt;room E349&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;11am&lt;/strong&gt;. Our guest speaker will be
&lt;strong&gt;Fabien Lacasa&lt;/strong&gt; from the Institut d’Astrophysique Spatiale (Orsay,
France).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 11:00, room E349, Fabien Lacasa (IAS), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cosmology-with-the-cosmic-web-the-high-resolution-promise&quot;&gt;Cosmology with the cosmic web: the high resolution promise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The large scale structure of the Universe, the cosmic web, is a key
probe for late-time cosmology, and is indeed targeted by several of
the major observational efforts in the coming decades. However, its
analysis is hampered by the complex non-linear dynamics it undergoes
as structure grow. A lot of efforts has focused on the impact of
non-linearity on the observables, in particular the power
spectrum. However, the non-linearity also affects error bars, and thus
the information content, by generating non-Gaussian tails that induce
new covariance term. After sufficient introduction, I will present a
first exhaustive derivation of the covariance of the galaxy angular
power spectrum. The impact will then be presented for a baseline
cosmological analysis up to mildly non-linear scale, showing
decreasing returns. By contrast, I will finally show that there is a
large motivation to jump more boldly and push into the strongly
non-linear regime at high resolution.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">The next cosmology seminar takes place on Thursday 7th of April, seminar room E349 at 11am. Our guest speaker will be Fabien Lacasa from the Institut d’Astrophysique Spatiale (Orsay, France).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gravitational multifield dynamics on Higgs pre-inflation and preheating</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2022/03/08/2202.07604.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gravitational multifield dynamics on Higgs pre-inflation and preheating" /><published>2022-03-08T09:42:07+01:00</published><updated>2022-03-08T09:42:07+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2022/03/08/2202.07604</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2022/03/08/2202.07604.html">&lt;p&gt;Traditionally the problem of initial conditions for inflation has been
treated separately from studies of reheating. To allow for a
parametric-type reheating, the inflaton must be allowed to interact
with (or decay to) other fields, and, these interactions should be
present also during inhomogeneous preinflation. Could they prevent
cosmic inflation to start in the first place?  In a single-author
publication &lt;a href=&quot;/members/joana.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cristian&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; answers this question
for Higgs Inflation: once more, inflation always starts and passes the
challenge!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inflationary paradigm postulates an early phase of accelerated
expansion of the Universe. Such a period provides an explanation for
the observed large-scale homogeneity and flatness in the cosmos.
After the end of inflation, the universe would have gone through a
phase where the energy of the inflaton is transferred to Standard
Model particles, heating up the universe and leading to a bath of
ultra-relativistic particles behaving like radiation.  This phase is
known as reheating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally the problem of initial condition for inflation, i.e.,
knowing if inflation can start from highly inhomogeneous initial
conditions, has been treated separately from studies of
reheating. However, they are connected. To allow for the so-called
parametric-type reheating, through resonances occurring while the
system is oscillating at the bottom of the potential, the inflaton
must be microscopically coupled to other fields. So, again, one could
raise the question: shouldn’t these interactions be present also
during inhomogeneous preinflation? Do they prevent cosmic inflation
to start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a previous paper, see Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#joana:2020rxm&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, we have
studied the robustness of &lt;em&gt;single-field&lt;/em&gt; Higgs Inflation to
inhomogeneous initial conditions of all sizes. We have paid attention
to include the gravitational dynamics of the system, showing the possible
formation of pre-inflationary black holes, as well as the generation
of shear/tensor modes in the metric. In short, we have showed that
these gravitational dynamics can only delay the beginning of inflation, but
never prevent it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Ref. &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#joana:2022uwc&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/members/joana.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cristian&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
expands the previous settings by adding an extra field into the Higgs
Inflation model. This field is coupled such that it allows for a
reheating of the Universe. Reheating is actually successful for a
range of the field-field interaction strength, which is numerically
explored in full General Relativity simulations. Then the same model
is confronted to various preinflationary inhomogeneous settings and the
full gravitational and scalar-field dynamics are investigated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure below shows the preheating resonances for the auxiliary
field (left panel). Structure formation occurs \(2\)-\(3\) e-folds
after the end of inflation (right panel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2202.07604/Reh_01.png&quot; alt=&quot;reh&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the exact same model during the inhomogeneous multi-field
preinflationary epochs, we confirm that the Higgs non-minimal coupling
to gravity acts as a stabilizer as it &lt;em&gt;washes out&lt;/em&gt; the energy
contribution of the other minimally coupled matter/scalar-field
sectors. In Ref &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#joana:2022uwc&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, it is shown that this occurs
naturally when one canonically normalizes the fields in the Einstein
frame. This effect generalizes the dynamics of inhomogeneous
extra-matter components, making them sub-dominant in comparison to the
inflaton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2202.07604/mf_preinf.png&quot; alt=&quot;preinf&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above figure illustrates the gravitational and scalar-field
dynamics during pre-inflation. Two simulations are shown, one with
super-Hubble initial conditions (left) and another with sub-Hubble
size inhomogeneities (right).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, these investigations further confirm the robustness of
Higgs Inflation to multi-field inhomogeneous initial conditions, while
putting in evidence the formation of complex structures during the
reheating. The possible production of compact objects during the
reheating, such as primordial black holes, will be investigated in
future works.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">Traditionally the problem of initial conditions for inflation has been treated separately from studies of reheating. To allow for a parametric-type reheating, the inflaton must be allowed to interact with (or decay to) other fields, and, these interactions should be present also during inhomogeneous preinflation. Could they prevent cosmic inflation to start in the first place? In a single-author publication Cristian answers this question for Higgs Inflation: once more, inflation always starts and passes the challenge!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2021/11/22/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2021-11-22T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-11-22T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2021/11/22/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2021/11/22/seminar.html">&lt;p&gt;Our next cosmology seminar takes place on &lt;strong&gt;Wednesday 1st&lt;/strong&gt; of December,
seminar &lt;strong&gt;room E349&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;2pm&lt;/strong&gt;. The speaker is &lt;strong&gt;Maxence Corman&lt;/strong&gt;
from the Perimeter Institute (Waterloo, Canada).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 14:00, room E349, Maxence Corman (PI), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;evolving-black-holes-in-a-nonsingular-bouncing-universe&quot;&gt;Evolving black holes in a nonsingular bouncing universe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One of the main unanswered questions of theoretical cosmology is
whether the universe emerged from a big bang followed by a period of
inflation or whether it had no beginning at all and bounced from a
period of slow contraction to the current expanding phase.  It has
been shown recently that it is possible for the universe to undergo a
nonsingular bounce at energies well below the Planck scale such that
the entire evolution can be treated classically. It is however still
unclear how to treat the passage of any pre-existing black holes
through the bounce to the expanding phase.  In this talk, we use
numerical techniques to consider the classical evolution of a black
hole in a non-singular universe driven by a ``ghost’’ scalar field. We
find that at least for small enough black holes, the black hole passes
through the bounce freely, albeit losing energy in the process.
Pushing this further, we also show that if the Hubble patch during
contraction shrinks to a size comparable or smaller than the radius of
the black hole this gives rise to interesting dynamics such as
disappearing and re-emerging horizons.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">Our next cosmology seminar takes place on Wednesday 1st of December, seminar room E349 at 2pm. The speaker is Maxence Corman from the Perimeter Institute (Waterloo, Canada).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2021/11/15/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2021-11-15T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-11-15T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2021/11/15/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2021/11/15/seminar.html">&lt;p&gt;Our next cosmology seminar takes place on &lt;strong&gt;Friday 19th&lt;/strong&gt; of November,
seminar &lt;strong&gt;room E349&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;2pm&lt;/strong&gt;. The speaker is &lt;strong&gt;Danilo Artigas&lt;/strong&gt;
from the Institut d’Astrophysique Spatiale (Paris, France) and Quantum
Cosmos Lab (Cracow, Poland).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 14:00, room E349, Danilo Artigas (IAS), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hamiltonian-formalism-for-cosmological-perturbations-the-separate-universe-approach&quot;&gt;Hamiltonian formalism for cosmological perturbations: the separate-universe approach&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In order to describe inhomogeneities and anisotropies in the Universe,
one generally considers a Friedmann-Lemaître-Robertson-Walker
background and introduces perturbations on top of it. Such a method is
commonly used in Lagrangian formalism and is fundamental for example
in order to describe the formation of large-scale structures. On the
other hand, the so-called “separate-universe” approach aims to provide
an effective description of cosmological perturbations at large
scales. In this talk, we will formulate the perturbation theory and
the separate universe approach in the Hamiltonian language. We will
then compare both frameworks to determine the domain of validity of
the separate universe. As expected, both match at large scales since
anisotropic degrees of freedom decouple from homogeneous ones. We’ll
finish discussing the gauge matching between both approaches and the
construction of their gauge-invariant quantities.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">Our next cosmology seminar takes place on Friday 19th of November, seminar room E349 at 2pm. The speaker is Danilo Artigas from the Institut d’Astrophysique Spatiale (Paris, France) and Quantum Cosmos Lab (Cracow, Poland).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">~~Post-doctoral opening in Cosmology~~</title><link href="https://curl.group/jobs/2021/10/22/IISN.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="~~Post-doctoral opening in Cosmology~~" /><published>2021-10-22T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-22T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/jobs/2021/10/22/IISN</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/jobs/2021/10/22/IISN.html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://uclouvain.be/en/research-institutes/irmp&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Institute of Mathematics and
Physics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is
openening a post-doctoral research position in the field of Cosmology
starting fall 2022 to work in collaboration with Prof. M. Drewes
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://cp3.phys.ucl.ac.be&quot;&gt;CP3&lt;/a&gt;) and Prof. Ch. Ringeval
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://curl.irmp.ucl.ac.be&quot;&gt;CURL&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applicants interested in early universe cosmology, such as cosmic
inflation, reheating, connection with particle physics as well as
future cosmological observations (CMB-S4, Euclid, LiteBird, LISA…),
are particularly encouraged to apply. Please notice that applicants
should have obtained their PhD no longer than 5 years before the
starting date of the fellowship, plus one year of allowance for
parenthood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letters of application (including a curriculum vitae, a list of
publications, a brief statement of research interests) and at least
two recommendation letters from senior scientists should be submitted
on-line, by the 15th of December 2021, at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cp3.irmp.ucl.ac.be/jobs/74&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;https://cp3.irmp.ucl.ac.be/jobs/74&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, or postal applications, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;christophe.ringeval@uclouvain.be
Cosmology, Universe and Relativity at Louvain
Institute of Mathematics and Physics
Louvain University
2, Chemin du Cyclotron
1348 Louvain-la-Neuve
Belgium
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of our current interests can be consulted on the CURL
website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://curl.group&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;curl.group&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Jobs" /><summary type="html">The Institute of Mathematics and Physics is openening a post-doctoral research position in the field of Cosmology starting fall 2022 to work in collaboration with Prof. M. Drewes (CP3) and Prof. Ch. Ringeval (CURL).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From quantum fluctuations to galaxies</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2021/10/15/CAAPC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From quantum fluctuations to galaxies" /><published>2021-10-15T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-15T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2021/10/15/CAAPC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2021/10/15/CAAPC.html">&lt;p&gt;C. Ringeval gives a public lecture on Cosmic Inflation for the Cercle
des Astronomes Amateurs de Charleroi (starts at 7:45pm). More information at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://caapc.be/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CAAPC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;linflation-cosmique-du-vide-quantique-aux-galaxies&quot;&gt;L’Inflation Cosmique: du vide quantique aux galaxies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Les mesures astronomiques et cosmologiques de ce début de siècle ont
permis de déterminer avec une précision redoutable la nature et les
abondances de toutes les formes d’énergie présentes dans l’Univers.
Elles ont, une fois de plus, donné raison au modèle du Big-Bang de
George Lemaître. Celui-ci décrit donc, avec précision, notre Univers
sur des distances allant jusqu’à la dizaine de gigaparsecs et nous
permet de comprendre son histoire dès la seconde après la singularité
initiale.  Cependant, nous verrons comment ces mesures posent aussi
des questions surprenantes sur l’évolution de l’Univers dans son
premier milliardième de seconde d’existence. Nous expliquerons
pourquoi la plus plausible des réponses est l’Inflation
Cosmique. Celle-ci nous dit que l’Univers eut été en accélération
quasi-exponentielle, dénué de toute de matière et lumière, gorgé de
fluctuations quantiques et d’ondes gravitationnelles : les embryons
des galaxies d’aujourd’hui.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/inflation_Charleroi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;CAAPC_first_slide&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">C. Ringeval gives a public lecture on Cosmic Inflation for the Cercle des Astronomes Amateurs de Charleroi (starts at 7:45pm). More information at CAAPC.</summary></entry></feed>