<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://curl.group/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://curl.group/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-07-10T12:02:32+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/</id><title type="html">CURL</title><subtitle>Research Group</subtitle><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><entry><title type="html">Two cosmology seminars in a row!</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2018/06/27/seminars.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two cosmology seminars in a row!" /><published>2018-06-27T14:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-27T14:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2018/06/27/seminars</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2018/06/27/seminars.html">&lt;p&gt;This Wednesday, we have not one but two cosmology seminars in a row!
We have the pleasure to receive &lt;strong&gt;Mateo Martinelli&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Alkistis Pourtsidou&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 13:00, Mateo Martinelli (Leiden U., Euclid), will be talking about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;future-constraints-on-parametrized-modified-gravity-the-impact-of-non-linear-scales-and-of-theoretical-priors&quot;&gt;Future constraints on parametrized modified gravity: the impact of	non linear scales and of theoretical priors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this talk I will present forecasted constraints on
Modified Gravity using Galaxy Clustering and Weak Lensing
measurements. I will explore different possible phenomenological
parametrizations for Modified Gravity models, encoding the effects of
these modifications in two generic functions (η and μ) of time and
space which affect the Poisson equation and the so-called
gravitational slip. I will focus on forecasts for future surveys and I
will highlight the constraining power gained when including non linear
scales in the analysis using phenomenological prescription for the
modelling of these scales in the Modified Gravity framework.  I will
then discuss how it is possible to connect phenomenological
parameterizations to viable theories of modified gravity, imposing
theoretical conditions on the reconstructed functions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a coffee break, at 14:30, Alkistis Pourtsidou (Queen Mary U.,
SKA, Euclid) will talk about&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cosmology-with-neutral-hydrogen-hi-intensity-mapping&quot;&gt;Cosmology with neutral hydrogen (HI) intensity mapping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I will introduce the innovative technique of HI intensity
mapping, which allows for precise cosmological measurements in the
radio wavelength. After talking about the current status of intensity
mapping measurements, I will focus on forthcoming surveys using
instruments like MeerKAT/SKA and CHIME to probe dark energy as well as
galaxy evolution. I will also present synergies between optical galaxy
and radio intensity mapping surveys in order to probe dark energy and
gravity, mitigate systematic effects, calibrate photometric redshifts,
and measure primordial non-gaussianity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">This Wednesday, we have not one but two cosmology seminars in a row! We have the pleasure to receive Mateo Martinelli and Alkistis Pourtsidou.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An invitation to grand-parents and their grand-children to discover together the secrets of our Universe</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/06/04/UDA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An invitation to grand-parents and their grand-children to discover together the secrets of our Universe" /><published>2018-06-04T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-04T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/06/04/UDA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/06/04/UDA.html">&lt;p&gt;The 4th of July, Sébastien will be presenting two outreach activities
dedicated to children and their grand-parents, organized by the
&lt;em&gt;Université des Aînés&lt;/em&gt; of UCLouvain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.universitedesaines.be/fiche-formation.php?categorie=435&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L’Univers selon les petits: Alice et le Big-Bang (6-10
ans)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.universitedesaines.be/fiche-formation.php?categorie=444&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L’Univers selon les grands: les plus belles images de l’Univers
(+10
ans)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/smile.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;smile&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">The 4th of July, Sébastien will be presenting two outreach activities dedicated to children and their grand-parents, organized by the Université des Aînés of UCLouvain.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Article in the astronomy magazine “Astrosurf”</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/06/01/ASM92.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Article in the astronomy magazine &quot;Astrosurf&quot;" /><published>2018-06-01T13:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-01T13:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/06/01/ASM92</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/06/01/ASM92.html">&lt;p&gt;Following our exploration of using small non-professional telescopes
for optical follow-up of Planck cluster candidates, see Ref. &lt;a href=&quot;#boucher:2018xvk&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/news/2018/01/01/1801.04124.html&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;, we have published an article entitled
“Mesure du redshift d’amas de galaxies” in the French astronomy
magazine &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.astrosurf.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Astrosurf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/ASM92_Sommaire_1200.png&quot; alt=&quot;astrosurf&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">Following our exploration of using small non-professional telescopes for optical follow-up of Planck cluster candidates, see Ref. [1] and this post, we have published an article entitled “Mesure du redshift d’amas de galaxies” in the French astronomy magazine Astrosurf.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Primordial vs Astrophysical Origin of Black Holes</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2018/05/18/PBHCERN.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Primordial vs Astrophysical Origin of Black Holes" /><published>2018-05-18T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-18T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2018/05/18/PBHCERN</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2018/05/18/PBHCERN.html">&lt;p&gt;From May 14th to 18th, S. Clesse is organizing the first international
conference dedicated to primordial black holes, held at CERN, Geneva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information, slides and recording of the presentations, are
available &lt;a href=&quot;https://indico.cern.ch/event/686745/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">From May 14th to 18th, S. Clesse is organizing the first international conference dedicated to primordial black holes, held at CERN, Geneva.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Des trous noirs nés une milli-seconde après le Big-Bang</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/05/04/maphyl.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Des trous noirs nés une milli-seconde après le Big-Bang" /><published>2018-05-04T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-04T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/05/04/maphyl</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/05/04/maphyl.html">&lt;p&gt;Lecture by S. Clesse, invited by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.maphyl.com&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MaPhyl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; ASBL (association of alumini
students of the UCL in Mathematics and Physics).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;French abstract: &lt;em&gt;La détection d’ondes gravitationnelles issues de la
fusion de trous noirs par l’expérience LIGO/VIRGO, couronnée du Prix
Nobel de Physique 2017, ouvre une nouvelle ère de l’astronomie
moderne.  Déjà, ces détections ont ravivé le débat sur la nature de la
matière noire.  Elles semblent indiquer la présence d’une population
inattendue de trous noirs dont l’abondance est étrangement compatible
avec celle de la matière noire, dont la nature est encore aujourd’hui
un des grands mystères de la cosmologie.  Ainsi, la matière noire
pourraient être constituée de trous noirs primordiaux formés moins
d’une milli-seconde après le Big-Bang.  Aujourd’hui une série d’autres
observations tendent à corroborer cette hypothèse.  Les détecteurs
d’ondes gravitationnelles de nouvelle génération, tels le Einstein
Telescope qui pourrait être construit à la frontière entre la
Belgique, les Pays-Bas et l’Allemagne, auront la capacité de vérifier,
ou invalider cette hypothèse.  Ils testeront aussi notre compréhension
de l’Univers primordial et de la physique fondamentale à des échelles
d’énergie jusqu’à présent inaccessibles.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">Lecture by S. Clesse, invited by the MaPhyl ASBL (association of alumini students of the UCL in Mathematics and Physics).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">La Cosmologie (pour les nuls)</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/05/02/kotastro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="La Cosmologie (pour les nuls)" /><published>2018-05-02T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-02T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/05/02/kotastro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/05/02/kotastro.html">&lt;p&gt;Public lecture by S. Clesse, organized by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kotastro.be&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kot Astro&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the UCLouvain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;French abstract: &lt;em&gt;Que se passe-t-il si l’on tombe dans un trou noir?
Est-il possible de voyager dans le temps? Qu’y avait-il avant le
Big-Bang? Où s’est-il produit, et dans quoi l’Univers s’étend-il
aujourd’hui? L’Univers a-t-il un bord? Existe-t-il d’autres Univers,
d’autres dimensions?  Lorsqu’on discute cosmologie et astrophysique,
ces questions pas si saugrenues reviennent sans cesse. Difficile de
faire la différence entre mythe et réalité, entre scénarios réalistes
et spéculations, entre science et fiction. Nous vous proposons un
voyage un peu fou aux frontières de la Science. Il vous permettra d’y
voir un peu plus clair et de faire le point sur les connaissances et
les défis d’aujourd’hui. Nous lèverons un coin du voile sur notre
Univers, parfois mystérieux, toujours surprenant…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/kot_astro.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;kotastro&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: Typographie conforme à la norme &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ex-abrupto.be/quelle-norme-typographique-suivre/&quot;&gt;NBN Z01-002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">Public lecture by S. Clesse, organized by the Kot Astro of the UCLouvain.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Printemps des Sciences</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/03/25/PDS.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Printemps des Sciences" /><published>2018-03-25T15:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-03-25T15:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/03/25/PDS</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/03/25/PDS.html">&lt;p&gt;From March 19th to 25th, Sébastien took part to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://uclouvain.be/fr/decouvrir/scinfuse/printemps-des-sciences.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Printemps des
Sciences&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
event, an entire week dedicated to science outreach for children and
youths in Belgium.  Two activities were proposed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Alice et le Big-Bang&lt;/em&gt;, about two hundreds children from 6 to 10
discovered the secrets of cells, atoms, stars, galaxies and the
Universe, back to the Big-Bang.  This activity obtained the best mark
in the evaluations provided by accompagnying teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second activity took the form of a public lecture dedicated to
secondary school students, on Black Holes, the Big-Bang and the
Universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/PDS.png&quot; alt=&quot;pds&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/Alice_BB.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;alice&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">From March 19th to 25th, Sébastien took part to the Printemps des Sciences event, an entire week dedicated to science outreach for children and youths in Belgium. Two activities were proposed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lecture for an internship in amateur astronomy</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/03/18/Modave.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lecture for an internship in amateur astronomy" /><published>2018-03-18T14:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-18T14:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/03/18/Modave</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/03/18/Modave.html">&lt;p&gt;S. Clesse presented in Modave, Belgium, a public lecture entitled (in
French) &lt;em&gt;Trous noirs, Big-Bang et Univers: voyage aux frontières du
savoir !&lt;/em&gt;, for an intership in amateur astronomy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">S. Clesse presented in Modave, Belgium, a public lecture entitled (in French) Trous noirs, Big-Bang et Univers: voyage aux frontières du savoir !, for an intership in amateur astronomy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Matière noire: la piste des trous noirs</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/01/31/PLS.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Matière noire: la piste des trous noirs" /><published>2018-01-31T14:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-31T14:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2018/01/31/PLS</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2018/01/31/PLS.html">&lt;p&gt;Together with a collaborator from UAM-IFT (Madrid), Juan
Garcia-Bellido, we have recently published an article in the French
science outreach magazine &lt;em&gt;Pour la Science&lt;/em&gt;, entitled &lt;em&gt;Matière noire:
la piste des trous noirs&lt;/em&gt;.  This article is available
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pourlascience.fr/sd/cosmologie/matiere-noire-la-piste-des-trous-noirs-10075.php&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
For the original English version, published in the &lt;em&gt;Scientific
American&lt;/em&gt;, see
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/is-dark-matter-made-of-black-holes/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/outreach/PBH.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;zphot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, &lt;a href=&quot;#garcia-bellido:2017nmv&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;  we review and explain the recent observations
pointing towards the possilbe existence of massive primordial black
holes, born less than one milli-second after the Big-Bang.  Such
primordial black holes could explain the origin of the Dark Matter in
the Universe and provide the seeds of the super-massive black holes at
the center of galaxies.  Finding a firm observational evidence for
even a single primordial black hole would revolutionize our
understanding of the early Universe, and might help to resolve
long-standing problems of cosmology and astrophysics.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html">Together with a collaborator from UAM-IFT (Madrid), Juan Garcia-Bellido, we have recently published an article in the French science outreach magazine Pour la Science, entitled Matière noire: la piste des trous noirs. This article is available here. For the original English version, published in the Scientific American, see here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Einstein Telescope meeting</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2018/01/29/ET.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Einstein Telescope meeting" /><published>2018-01-29T09:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-29T09:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2018/01/29/ET</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2018/01/29/ET.html">&lt;p&gt;The University of Liège is hosting the 9th COSPA meeting on 31 January 2018, which will be focused on the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.et-gw.eu/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Einstein Telescope&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Program available on their
&lt;a href=&quot;https://events.uliege.be/telescope-einstein/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html">The University of Liège is hosting the 9th COSPA meeting on 31 January 2018, which will be focused on the Einstein Telescope.</summary></entry></feed>