<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://curl.group/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://curl.group/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-04-18T18:28:39+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/feed.xml</id><title type="html">CURL</title><subtitle>Research Group</subtitle><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><entry><title type="html">Interview for Quanta Magazine</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2024/04/18/QuantaMag.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview for Quanta Magazine" /><published>2024-04-18T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-04-18T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2024/04/18/QuantaMag</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2024/04/18/QuantaMag.html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/members/auclair"><strong>Pierre</strong></a> gave an interview for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quanta_Magazine"><strong>Quanta
Magazine</strong></a> in an
article dedicated to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laser_Interferometer_Space_Antenna"><strong>LISA</strong></a> mission.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/hopes-of-big-bang-discoveries-ride-on-a-future-spacecraft-20240417/"><strong>Hopes of Big Bang Discoveries Ride on a Future Spacecraft</strong></a></p>

<p>More details can be found in the scientific paper Ref. <a class="citation" href="#colpi:2024xhw">[1]</a> and this <a href="/news/2024/01/25/LISA.html"><strong>post</strong></a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Pierre gave an interview for Quanta Magazine in an article dedicated to the LISA mission.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Insights into the Clustering Behaviour of Primordial Black Holes</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2024/04/10/2402.00600.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Insights into the Clustering Behaviour of Primordial Black Holes" /><published>2024-04-10T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-04-10T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2024/04/10/2402.00600</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2024/04/10/2402.00600.html"><![CDATA[<p>Are primordial black holes already clustered in the early universe?
In a recent publication, <a href="/members/blachier"><strong>Baptiste</strong></a> and
<a href="/members/auclair"><strong>Pierre</strong></a> tackle the clustering problem of these
enigmatic objects using an excursion-set approach to deal with the
so-called “cloud-in-cloud” mechanism.</p>

<p>Primordial black holes (PBH) are cosmological objects that could have
been formed in the earliest instants of the universe’s history, for
instance, when large overdensities collapse under their own gravity.
Understanding how these PBHs cluster is essential as it can provide
insights into the evolution of structure formation in the universe and
could potentially help in assessing how much, and when, binaries of
these objects appear.</p>

<p>In Ref. <a class="citation" href="#auclair:2024jwj">[1]</a>, <a href="/members/auclair"><strong>Pierre</strong></a>
and <a href="/members/blachier"><strong>Baptiste</strong></a> have used the excursion-set
formalism to quantify the initial spatial clustering of PBHs generated
from large Gaussian density fluctuations. Their method takes into
account the “cloud-in-cloud” mechanism, which is a critical aspect
that is overlooked in studies using the Poisson model of clustering.</p>

<p>In the excursion-set formalism, the collapse of an overdensity to form
a PBH of mass \(M\) is recast into the probability of finding the
first crossing of a random walk at some scale \(S(M)\). This approach
has been already applied to study the formation of large-scale
structure, in which multiple crossings of a random walk describe a
hierarchy of structures. This formalism was first developed to solve
the “cloud-in-cloud” problem, that is resolving this hierarchy of
structures.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2402.00600/spread.png" alt="spread" /></p>

<p>The cloud-in-cloud mechanism implies that PBHs should be part of
larger structures: they don’t just appear randomly as per the Poisson
assumption. This results in a natural and intrinsic correlation
between the formation of pairs of PBHs, which is important for
accurately modelling the clustering behaviour at small scales. The
following picture shows two random walks that share a common past
until the “time” \(S_{r}\): they come from the same realisation of a
large scale density perturbation. Subsequently, they evolve in
distinct ways and this results in two different collapses that occur
respectively at the first-crossing times \(S_{1}\) and \(S_{2}\)</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2402.00600/duo.png" alt="duo" /></p>

<p>Such an approach automatically includes short-range exclusion effects:
PBHs are anti-correlated at short distances!</p>

<p>The authors also present explicit expressions for the excess
probability to find pairs of PBHs separated by a given distance and
for the excess probability to find pairs with an asymmetric mass
ratio.</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are primordial black holes already clustered in the early universe? In a recent publication, Baptiste and Pierre tackle the clustering problem of these enigmatic objects using an excursion-set approach to deal with the so-called “cloud-in-cloud” mechanism.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Le télescope spatial Euclid</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2024/03/23/CAO.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Le télescope spatial Euclid" /><published>2024-03-23T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-03-23T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2024/03/23/CAO</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2024/03/23/CAO.html"><![CDATA[<p>Lors de la semaine du <a href="https://www.printempsdessciencesucl.be/evenement/7/activite/803"><strong>Printemps des
Sciences</strong></a>,
<a href="/members/chris.html"><strong>Christophe</strong></a> donne une conférence publique sur le télescope spatial
Euclid pour le Club d’Astronomie de Ottignies Louvain-la-Neuve
(8:00pm). Plus d’informations sur le site du <a href="http://www.caolln.be/"><strong>CAO</strong></a>.</p>

<h3 id="le-télescope-spatial-euclid-et-les-implications-attendues-pour-lunivers-primordial">Le télescope spatial Euclid et les implications attendues pour l’univers primordial</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/images/outreach/euclid_cao.jpg" alt="CAO banner" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lors de la semaine du Printemps des Sciences, Christophe donne une conférence publique sur le télescope spatial Euclid pour le Club d’Astronomie de Ottignies Louvain-la-Neuve (8:00pm). Plus d’informations sur le site du CAO.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">LISA is adopted</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2024/01/25/LISA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LISA is adopted" /><published>2024-01-25T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-25T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2024/01/25/LISA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2024/01/25/LISA.html"><![CDATA[<p>On this historic day, the European Space Agency
(<a href="https://www.esa.int"><strong>ESA</strong></a>) gave
<a href="https://www.esa.int/Science_Exploration/Space_Science/Capturing_the_ripples_of_spacetime_LISA_gets_go-ahead"><strong>approval</strong></a>
to
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laser_Interferometer_Space_Antenna"><strong>LISA</strong></a>,
the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna. This decision marks a
significant milestone for the LISA mission as it signifies the
acceptance of its design and scientific goals.</p>

<p>LISA will be the next-generation observatory in the field of
gravitational waves, surpassing current terrestrial capabilities by
exploring lower frequencies and longer timescales, opening up a new
observation window into the universe.  and technological
innovation. The LISA definition study report, in which <a href="/members/auclair"><strong>Pierre</strong></a> was a
contributor, presents an in-depth analysis of the mission’s scientific
rationale, design, and implementation plans, see Ref. <a class="citation" href="#colpi:2024xhw">[1]</a>. It highlights the
groundbreaking discoveries that LISA is expected to make</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/outreach/LISA_motion.gif" alt="LISA spacecrafts" /></p>

<p>With ESA’s approval, the LISA mission moves one step closer to
reality!</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On this historic day, the European Space Agency (ESA) gave approval to LISA, the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna. This decision marks a significant milestone for the LISA mission as it signifies the acceptance of its design and scientific goals.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">~~Post-doctoral opening in Cosmology~~</title><link href="https://curl.group/jobs/2023/12/26/IISN.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="~~Post-doctoral opening in Cosmology~~" /><published>2023-12-26T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-26T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/jobs/2023/12/26/IISN</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/jobs/2023/12/26/IISN.html"><![CDATA[<p>We are pleased to announce the opening of another <strong>post-doctoral position</strong> in
Cosmology within the <a href="https://curl.group"><strong>CURL</strong></a> group at the
<a href="https://uclouvain.be/en/research-institutes/irmp"><strong>Institute of Mathematics and
Physics</strong></a>, Louvain
University (Belgium), starting fall 2024.</p>

<p>Applicants interested in early universe cosmology (cosmic inflation,
reheating, cosmic defects…), CMB, large scale structures, gravitational
waves cosmology, as well as data analysis for current and future
cosmological observations (CMB-S4, Euclid, LiteBird, LISA…), are
particularly encouraged to apply. A summary of our <a href="https://curl.group/publications.html"><strong>research
interests</strong></a> can be consulted
online.</p>

<p>Appointment is available for two years. Please notice that applicants
should have obtained their PhD no longer than 5 years before the
starting date of the fellowship, plus one year of allowance for
parenthood.</p>

<hr />

<p>Letters of application (including a curriculum vitae, a list of
publications, a brief statement of research interests) and at least
two recommendation letters from senior scientists should be submitted
on-line, by the 28th of January 2024, at:</p>

<p><a href="https://cp3.irmp.ucl.ac.be/job/94"><strong>https://cp3.irmp.ucl.ac.be/job/94</strong></a></p>

<p>For more information, or postal applications, please contact:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>christophe.ringeval@uclouvain.be
Cosmology, Universe and Relativity at Louvain
Institute of Mathematics and Physics
Louvain University
2, Chemin du Cyclotron
1348 Louvain-la-Neuve
Belgium
</code></pre></div></div>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Jobs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are pleased to announce the opening of another post-doctoral position in Cosmology within the CURL group at the Institute of Mathematics and Physics, Louvain University (Belgium), starting fall 2024.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">~~Post-doctoral opening in Cosmology with Euclid~~</title><link href="https://curl.group/jobs/2023/12/18/ESA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="~~Post-doctoral opening in Cosmology with Euclid~~" /><published>2023-12-18T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-18T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/jobs/2023/12/18/ESA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/jobs/2023/12/18/ESA.html"><![CDATA[<p>We are pleased to announce the opening of a <strong>post-doctoral position</strong> in
Cosmology, focused on the exploitation of the Euclid data, within the
<a href="https://curl.group"><strong>CURL</strong></a> group at the <a href="https://uclouvain.be/en/research-institutes/irmp"><strong>Institute of
Mathematics and
Physics</strong></a>, Louvain
University (Belgium), starting no later than fall 2024.</p>

<p>Applicants with expertises in cosmic inflation, large scale
structures, data analysis and Bayesian inference, skilled in
computing and analytics, are particularly encouraged to apply.</p>

<p>The position is supported by the Belgium Euclid Science
Exploitation <strong>ESA-Prodex</strong> research program which unifies
expertises between
<a href="https://research.ugent.be/web/person/sven-de-rijcke-0/en"><strong>Ugent</strong></a>
(Gent), <a href="https://www.astro.uliege.be/~sluse/"><strong>ULiege</strong></a> (Liège),
<a href="https://physth.ulb.be/people_SClesse.html"><strong>ULB</strong></a> (Brussels) and
<a href="https://curl.irmp.ucl.ac.be/members/chris.html"><strong>UCLouvain</strong></a>
(Louvain-la-Neuve) universities. There will be close collaborations
between these groups, computing and travelling support are excellent.</p>

<p>Appointment is available for three years.</p>

<hr />

<p>Letters of application (including a curriculum vitae, a list of
publications, a brief statement of research interests) and at least
two recommendation letters from senior scientists should be submitted
on-line, by the 28th of January 2024, at:</p>

<p><a href="https://cp3.irmp.ucl.ac.be/job/95"><strong>https://cp3.irmp.ucl.ac.be/job/95</strong></a></p>

<p>For more information, or postal applications, please contact:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>christophe.ringeval@uclouvain.be
Cosmology, Universe and Relativity at Louvain
Institute of Mathematics and Physics
Louvain University
2, Chemin du Cyclotron
1348 Louvain-la-Neuve
Belgium
</code></pre></div></div>

<hr />]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Jobs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are pleased to announce the opening of a post-doctoral position in Cosmology, focused on the exploitation of the Euclid data, within the CURL group at the Institute of Mathematics and Physics, Louvain University (Belgium), starting no later than fall 2024.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spatial Curvature from Super-Hubble Cosmological Fluctuations</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2023/12/01/2302.14530.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spatial Curvature from Super-Hubble Cosmological Fluctuations" /><published>2023-12-01T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-01T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2023/12/01/2302.14530</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2023/12/01/2302.14530.html"><![CDATA[<p>Could cosmological perturbations stretched over distances larger than
the size of the observable Universe modify the shape of our
space-time? <a href="/members/blachier.html"><strong>Baptiste</strong></a>,
<a href="/members/auclair.html"><strong>Pierre</strong></a>
and <a href="/members/chris.html"><strong>Christophe</strong></a>, in collaboration with
<a href="https://www.lpens.ens.psl.eu/vincent-vennin/?lang=en"><strong>Vincent Vennin</strong></a>, have
recently shown that this is the case through the spatial curvature.</p>

<p>It is a common Cosmologist’s intuition that cosmological fluctuations,
the tiny perturbations of amplitude \(10^{-5}\) at the origin of
galaxies, should induce some kind of noise on the cosmological
parameters. Is this quantifiable? Are super-Hubble cosmological
perturbations having an effect at all?</p>

<p>In Ref. <a class="citation" href="#blachier:2023ooc">[1]</a>, we show that arbitrarily long
perturbations have an observable effect. More precisely, the gradient
and Laplacian of these fluctuations are dynamically <strong>creating a
spatial curvature</strong> in the homogeneous and isotropic metric of local
observers. In the following picture, we sketch how one of these modes,
having a wavelength much larger than the observer’s Hubble radius, can
be “felt” through its gradient.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2302.14530/cosmograd.png" alt="grad" title="Super-Hubble gradient" /></p>

<p>It is not a few Hubble-sized fluctuations that contribute, but an infinite
number of super-Hubble modes, all those having wavelength larger than our observable
universe. Denoting by \(K\) the curvature of the FLRW spatial sections,
and \(\xi\) the sum of these constant modes, we find</p>

\[K = -\frac{2}{3} \Delta \xi - \frac{1}{3} \left(\nabla \xi \right)^2.\]

<p>However, because fluctuations are, by definition, of random nature, we
cannot predict a definite value for the curvature density parameter
\(\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}\). This one is now promoted to a stochastic
variable. Even though the sum of all super-Hubble modes averages to
zero, i.e. \(\langle \xi \rangle = 0\), we predict, for the standard
Gaussian and scale-invariant cosmological perturbations, a very small
non-vanishing value</p>

\[\langle \Omega_\mathrm{K_0} \rangle = -\frac{\langle K e^{-2\xi} \rangle}{a_0^2 H_0^2} = \frac{5}{6} \mathcal{P}_* \simeq 1.7 \times 10^{-9}.\]

<p>More importantly, because \(\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}\) is a stochastic
variable, it also fluctuates and its realizations are, in fact,
dictated by its standard deviation</p>

\[\sqrt{\langle{\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}^2}\rangle-\langle{\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}}\rangle^2} \simeq \dfrac{1}{3}
\sqrt{\mathcal{P}_*} \simeq 1.5 \times 10^{-5}.\]

<p>This is the <strong>typical value</strong> that any observer will measure <strong>at any
epoch</strong> during the cosmic history.</p>

<hr />

<p>But there is more. The spatial curvature of our local Hubble patch is
thus a measurable number that can tell us what is going on on the
largest possible length scales of the Universe, length scales that are
much larger than our Hubble volume. What if the infinite sum of very
large wavelength modes, \(\xi\) here, is no longer a small
quantity? Such a situation could very well be happening if the
Universe has experienced a period of stochastic inflation in its
infancy!</p>

<p>In Ref. <a class="citation" href="#blachier:2023ooc">[1]</a>, we have been able to estimate the
full probability distribution function for \(\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}\)
when cosmological fluctuations are generated by Cosmic Inflation. If
\(\xi\) remains small, it is a slightly distorted Gaussian
distribution with a typical width of \(10^{-5}\), as expected. But if
inflation last for a long period, enough for \(\xi\) to be of order
unity, the distribution becomes highly non-Gaussian, as represented in
the following figure (red curve)</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2302.14530/probomega_tails.jpg" alt="proba" title="Non-Gaussian probability distribution" /></p>

<p>In this plot, the black curve is what would be a Gaussian probability
distribution with same width. Clearly, large values of
\(\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}\) are now much more probable than what one could
have naively expected. Are we going to measure a non-vanishing
\(\Omega_\mathrm{K_0}\) in the future?</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Could cosmological perturbations stretched over distances larger than the size of the observable Universe modify the shape of our space-time? Baptiste, Pierre and Christophe, in collaboration with Vincent Vennin, have recently shown that this is the case through the spatial curvature.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2023/11/17/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2023-11-17T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-17T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2023/11/17/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2023/11/17/seminar.html"><![CDATA[<p>The next cosmology seminar takes place on <strong>Friday 24th</strong> of November,
seminar <strong>room E349</strong> at <strong>2pm</strong>. Our guest speaker will be <strong>Bryce
Cyr</strong> from the <a href="https://www.jodrellbank.manchester.ac.uk/"><strong>Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics</strong></a> at the University
of Manchester (Manchester, United Kingdom).</p>

<hr />

<p>At 2pm, room E349,  <strong>Bryce Cyr</strong> (University of Manchester), will be talking about</p>

<h3 id="synergies-between-gravitational-waves-and-cmb-spectral-distortions">Synergies between gravitational waves and CMB spectral distortions</h3>

<p><em>In this talk, I will discuss various ways in which distortions to the
 frequency spectrum of the cosmic microwave background can be used to
 place constraints on stochastic backgrounds of gravitational
 waves. After a brief overview of spectral distortion theory, I will
 show how enhancements to the small-scale primordial power spectrum of
 curvature perturbations can induce sizeable distortions. Even in the
 absence of enhancements, a nearly-scale invariant spectrum presents a
 target well within reach of next generation
 experiments. Additionally, I will highlight how the presence of
 primordial tensor modes will also lead to an inevitable (although
 small) distortion signature. I will then apply this formalism to a
 model of scalar induced gravitational waves (SIGWs), showcasing how
 constraints on the primordial scalar power spectrum can be mapped to
 the gravitational wave parameter space for these models. Time
 permitting, I will also show our updated formalism can be used to
 improve constraints on the parameter space of primordial black
 holes.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The next cosmology seminar takes place on Friday 24th of November, seminar room E349 at 2pm. Our guest speaker will be Bryce Cyr from the Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics at the University of Manchester (Manchester, United Kingdom).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cosmology Seminar</title><link href="https://curl.group/news/2023/10/11/seminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cosmology Seminar" /><published>2023-10-11T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-11T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/news/2023/10/11/seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/news/2023/10/11/seminar.html"><![CDATA[<p>The next cosmology seminar takes place on <strong>Thursday 2nd</strong> of
November, seminar <strong>room E349</strong> at <strong>2pm</strong>. Our guest speaker will be
<strong>Suvashis Maity</strong> from the Indian Institute of Technology (IIT)
Madras (Chennai, India).</p>

<hr />

<p>At 2pm, room E349,  Suvashis Maity (IIT Madras), will be talking about</p>

<h3 id="ultra-slow-roll-inflation-and-loop-corrections-to-the-scalar-power-spectrum">Ultra slow roll inflation and loop corrections to the scalar power spectrum</h3>

<p><em>Recently, there have been efforts to examine the contributions to the
 scalar power spectrum due to the loops arising from the cubic order
 terms in the action describing the perturbations, specifically in
 inflationary scenarios that permit a brief epoch of ultra slow roll
 (USR). A phase of USR inflation leads to significant observational
 consequences, such as the copious production of primordial black
 holes. In this talk, I shall discuss the loop contributions to the
 scalar power spectrum in scenarios of USR inflation arising due to
 the quartic order terms in the action describing the scalar
 perturbations. I shall initially describe the computation of the loop
 contributions to the scalar power spectrum due to the dominant term
 in the action at the quartic order. Thereafter, I shall consider a
 scenario wherein a phase of USR is sandwiched between two stages of
 slow roll inflation and describe the behavior of the loop
 contributions in situations involving late, intermediate and early
 epochs of USR. In the inflationary scenario involving a late phase of
 USR, for reasonable choices of the parameters, I shall show that the
 loop corrections are negligible for the entire range of wave
 numbers. In the intermediate case, the contributions from the loops
 prove to be scale invariant over large scales, and we find that these
 contributions can amount to 30% of the power spectrum at the leading
 order. In the case wherein USR sets in early, we find that the loop
 contributions could be negative and can dominate the power spectrum
 at the leading order, which indicates a breakdown of the perturbative
 expansion. I shall conclude with a brief summary and outlook.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="News" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The next cosmology seminar takes place on Thursday 2nd of November, seminar room E349 at 2pm. Our guest speaker will be Suvashis Maity from the Indian Institute of Technology (IIT) Madras (Chennai, India).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Découverte du fond stochastique d’ondes gravitationnelles</title><link href="https://curl.group/outreach/2023/07/03/SGWB.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Découverte du fond stochastique d’ondes gravitationnelles" /><published>2023-07-03T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-07-03T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://curl.group/outreach/2023/07/03/SGWB</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://curl.group/outreach/2023/07/03/SGWB.html"><![CDATA[<p>Plusieurs collaborations internationales en
<a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radioastronomie"><strong>radio-astronomie</strong></a>
viennent d’annoncer la première détection du <strong>fond stochastique
d’ondes gravitationnelles</strong>. <a href="/members/auclair.html"><strong>Pierre</strong></a> a
cosigné la publication de
l’<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_Pulsar_Timing_Array"><strong>EPTA</strong></a>.</p>

<p>Ce <strong>jeudi 29 Juin 2023</strong>, plusieurs collaborations internationales en
radio-astronomie,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_American_Nanohertz_Observatory_for_Gravitational_Waves"><strong>NANOGRAV</strong></a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_Pulsar_Timing_Array"><strong>EPTA</strong></a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parkes_Observatory#Parkes_Pulsar_Timing_Array"><strong>PPTA</strong></a>,
<a href="https://inpta.iitr.ac.in/"><strong>InPTA</strong></a> et
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five-hundred-meter_Aperture_Spherical_Telescope"><strong>CPTA</strong></a>,
ont annoncé avoir détecté indépendamment un <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravitational_wave_background"><strong>fond stochastique
d’ondes
gravitationnelles</strong></a>
dans une bande de fréquences située autour du milliardième de
Hertz. C’est une découverte majeure qui devrait nous permettre d’en
apprendre beaucoup sur la formation des galaxies et sur la physique a
l’œuvre dans tout l’Univers.</p>

<p>Les contributions de <a href="/members/auclair.html"><strong>Pierre</strong></a> à la
publication de EPTA, Ref. <a class="citation" href="#antoniadis:2023xlr">[1]</a>, concernent l’analyse des
différentes sources cosmologiques possibles, dont les
<strong>cordes cosmiques</strong>, un des domaines d’expertise de <a href="/"><strong>CURL</strong></a>.</p>

<p>Le <strong>fond stochastique d’ondes gravitationnelles</strong> est la
superposition de toutes les ondes gravitationnelles émises dans
l’univers. Par analogie avec le son, c’est comme si nous avions etendu
le brouhaha d’une foule sans toutefois parvenir à distinguer une
conversation en particulier. Ce bruit de fond est très intéressant car
il donne accès aux propriétés stochastiques et globales de toutes les
sources à la fois.</p>

<p>Tout aussi spectaculaire que cette découverte est la méthode utilisée
pour trouver ce fond d’ondes gravitationnelles. Point de détecteurs
terrestres ou spatiaux, mais des <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%89toile_%C3%A0_neutrons"><strong>étoiles à
neutrons</strong></a>
particulières. Une étoile à neutron est le cœur chaud et ulta-dense
qu’il reste après qu’une étoile supermassive (entre 10 et 20 fois la
masse du Soleil) ait explosé en supernova. La fameuse <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/N%C3%A9buleuse_du_Crabe"><strong>nébuleuse du
Crabe</strong></a>, un
rémanent de supernova, contient un pulsar en son centre.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/outreach/m1_HaSIIOIII_cut.jpg" alt="M1, la nébuleuse du Crabe" /></p>

<p>Les <strong>réseaux de pulsars millisecondes</strong>, ou <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pulsar_timing_array"><strong>Pulsar Timing
Arrays</strong></a> (PTA) en
anglais, utilisent des étoiles à neutrons tournant très rapidement sur
elles-même, plusieurs centaines de fois par seconde, qui émettent un
fort rayonnement dans la direction de leur axe magnétique. À la
manière d’un phare, le <strong>pulsar</strong> semble avoir une <em>pulsation</em> lorsque
ce rayonnement radio se trouve en direction de la Terre.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/outreach/pulsar.gif" alt="Un pulsar" /></p>

<p>La pulsation très régulière des pulsars en font des horloges célestes
extrêmement précises. En observant ces pulsars pendant plus de vingt ans
au moyen de radiotélescopes, et en notant soigneusement les petites
irrégularités dans les temps d’arrivée de leur flash, les
radioastronomes sont parvenus à mettre en évidence l’existence de ce
fond stochastique d’ondes gravitationnelles. En effet, lorsque ces
ondes gravitationnelles passent entre la Terre et les pulsars, elles
induisent des déformations de l’espace-temps qui laissent une
corrélation caractéristique entre les temps d’arrivée des flashs.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/outreach/hellings_downs_correlations.jpg" alt="Corrélations de Hellings and Downs" /></p>

<p>Si la nature “onde gravitationnelle” de ce signal est donc établie,
plusieurs interprétations sont néanmoins possibles concernant son
origine. L’hypothèse présentée comme la plus naturelle est celle d’un
fond stochastique dû à des binaires de trous noirs
supermassifs. D’autres propositions, comme les cordes cosmiques ou les
transitions de phases du premier ordre, permettraient aussi
d’expliquer les observations, avec d’importantes conséquences pour
notre compréhension des premiers instants de l’Univers.</p>]]></content><author><name>Chris Ringeval</name></author><category term="Outreach" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Plusieurs collaborations internationales en radio-astronomie viennent d’annoncer la première détection du fond stochastique d’ondes gravitationnelles. Pierre a cosigné la publication de l’EPTA.]]></summary></entry></feed>